<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<d:descs xmlns:d="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml">
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="teiCorpus"
           corresp="row_teiCorpus">
      <d:p>This element encloses the entire corpus and is the common ancestor of all other
         elements.</d:p>
      <d:p>XPath: /*</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="teiHeader"
           corresp="row_teiHeader">
      <d:p>This element contains metadata about a TEI file. Where used in corpus.xml, it contains
         data referenced by <d:c>@xml:id</d:c> from across the rest of the corpus. It includes names
         and other details of scribes and abbreviations, for example.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="fileDesc"
           corresp="row_fileDesc">
      <d:p>When a direct child of <d:c>teiHeader</d:c>, <d:c>fileDesc</d:c> contains bibliographical
         information about the file itself. It is also used within <d:c>msItem/biblFull</d:c> to
         contain a keyword list relating to the individual text; this latter structure is mostly
         unnecessary for the purposes of the corpus but is required for TEI conformance.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="titleStmt"
           corresp="row_titleStmt">
      <d:p>This contains the most basic bibliographical information about the work to which it
         relates, namely, the title and optionally details of anyone responsible.</d:p>
      <d:p>Where its parent is <d:c>teiHeader/fileDesc</d:c>, it provides details for the entire TEI
         file. When that file is corpus.xml, it contains the corpus title and a list of those who
         have worked on the corpus in various capacities. Where that file is a transcription file,
         it provides a title for the transcription and names the editor primarily responsible for
         that transcription, although it is likely that it has been reviewed by multiple team
         members in reality.</d:p>
      <d:p>Where its parent is <d:c>biblFull/fileDesc</d:c> (i.e. it relates to an individual text),
         it provides the title for that text.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="title"
           corresp="row_title">
      <d:p>This is used in a variety of contexts to contain the title of a file, bibliographical
         work, or a transcribed text within the corpus or a subsection thereof.</d:p>
      <d:p>Even where the <d:c>title</d:c> element appears within a transcription (e.g.
            <d:c>TEI/text/body/div/head/title</d:c>), it remains part of the editorial apparatus. In
         other words, the <d:c>title</d:c> element is never used to mark up titles that appear in
         manuscripts. For avoidance of doubt, the <d:c>title</d:c> element is also never used for a
         person's title.</d:p>
      <d:list>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@level</d:c> is only used in the context of a bibliography entry; it is used to
            differentiate a monograph title from the title of a multi-authored book in which the
            work being described appears, for example.</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@type</d:c> is also only used in the context of a bibliography entry, where it
            distinguishes a condensed version of a work's title from the full version.</d:item>
      </d:list>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="respStmt"
           corresp="row_respStmt">
      <d:p>The <d:c>respStmt</d:c> element contains other elements detailing one or more
         individuals' responsibility for a file or bibliographical work.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="name"
           corresp="row_name">
      <d:p>The <d:c>name</d:c> element is used in a variety of contexts to contain an anthroponym,
         toponym, demonym, or other sort of name.</d:p>
      <d:p>Where it appears within <cdoe>respStmt</cdoe>, it contains the name of an individual
         responsible for a file or bibliographical work. In this context, the name is split into
            <d:c>forename</d:c> and <d:c>surname</d:c>.</d:p>
      <d:p>Where it appears within a transcription (<d:c>text//name</d:c>), it is used to mark up
         the occurrence of a name in a transcription. In this context, it must contain at least one
            <d:c>w</d:c> element and could contain any of the markup used for transcribed text (e.g.
         unclear, space). If part or all of the name requires emendation, the <d:c>choice</d:c>
         element must be contained within <d:c>name</d:c> and not contain it. <d:c>name</d:c> can
         also contain a nested <d:c>name</d:c> element, where one <d:c>name</d:c> contains another
            <d:c>name</d:c> (e.g. Mael Coluim).</d:p>
      <d:p>The following attributes are in active use with <d:c>name</d:c>:</d:p>
      <d:list>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@id</d:c>: all <d:c>name</d:c> elements require this attribute to be compliant with
            the DASG schema.</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@xml:id</d:c>: when names of project members are given in <d:c>respStmt</d:c>
            elements in corpus.xml, they are assigned unique IDs via this attribute there. These IDS
            can be used to reference them elsewhere, usually using <d:c>@resp</d:c>.</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@type</d:c>: when the <d:c>name</d:c> element is used to mark up a name in a
            transcription, this identifies what sort of name it is (e.g. personal, place).</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@corresp</d:c>: when the <d:c>name</d:c> element is used to mark up a placename in
            a transcription, this attribute can be used to link to an entry for that name in an
            external placenames database (e.g. logainm.ie) via an URL. It can be used whether or not
            the word(s) in the name have also been linked to headwords and the same URL can be used
            here and for a contained word's <d:c>@lemmaRef</d:c>.</d:item>
      </d:list>
      <d:p>Other attributes (<d:c>@full</d:c>, <d:c>@instant</d:c>) are at the time of writing (July
         2021) assumed by the schema but are not actively used in the mark-up.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="resp"
           corresp="row_resp">
      <d:p>
         <d:c>resp</d:c> is used within respStmt to describe a responsibility belonging to the
         person named in the sibling <d:c>name</d:c> element.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="publicationStmt"
           corresp="row_publicationStmt">
      <d:p>When used in the <d:code>fileDesc</d:code> element relating to a TEI file, this element
         contains information relating to the publication of the file and its contents, such as who
         is responsbile for it and any restrictions on its use.</d:p>
      <d:p>When used in the <d:code>fileDesc</d:code> element relating to a text item from a
         transcription (<d:code>msItem/biblFull/fileDesc/publicationStmt</d:code>), this element
         simply contains the statement that the item is a "Draft transcription"; publication is
         already provided by the <d:code>publicationStmt</d:code> at file level.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="authority"
           corresp="row_authority">
      <d:p>
         <d:c>authority</d:c> refers to the body responsible for the file and its
         publication.</d:p>
      <d:p>In corpus.xml, this element contains the contact details for the Faclair na Gàidhlig
         project and is identified with the <d:c>@xml:id</d:c> "authority". Elsewhere, this element
         links to these details via <d:c>@sameAs="authority"</d:c>.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="address"
           corresp="row_address">
      <d:p>This contains contact details for the Faclair na Gàidhlig project, comprised of a series
            <d:c>addrLine</d:c> elements.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="addrLine"
           corresp="row_addrLine">
      <d:p>This contains a line of the street address for the Faclair na Gàidhlig project.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="email"
           corresp="row_email">
      <d:p>This contains an email address for the Faclair na Gàidhlig project.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="num"
           corresp="row_num">
      <d:p>The meaning of this element varies depending on context.</d:p>
      <d:p>When it appears within <d:c>addrLine</d:c>, it contains a telephone number for the
         Faclair na Gàidhlig project.</d:p>
      <d:p>When it appears within a transcription, it is used to mark up a number that cannot be
         tagged as a single word and link to a dictionary headword or where the number appears in a
         manuscript as apparatus rather than in a syntactic context.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="availability"
           corresp="row_availability">
      <d:p>This contains information on how the file can be used. This is set to "restricted" via
            <d:c>status</d:c> and contains the following (within <d:c>p</d:c>): "For internal use by
         the Faclair na Gàidhlig/DASG projects." </d:p>
      <d:p>The attribute <d:c>@default</d:c> is at the time of writing (July 2021) assumed by the
         schema but is not actively used in the mark-up.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="p"
           corresp="row_p">
      <d:p>
         <d:c>p</d:c> is a very widely used element. It is used to contain text belonging in a
         single paragraph.</d:p>
      <d:p>In corpus.xml and in the <d:c>teiHeader</d:c> of transcription files and the hwData file,
         it is used to organise prose metadata added by editors.</d:p>
      <d:p>Within transcriptions (<d:c>text//p</d:c>), it is used to contain transcribed prose. A
         new <d:c>p</d:c> element is begun when the text switches back from verse to prose, when the
         scribe visually indicates a major new subdivision of a prose text, or if the editors feel a
         new paragraph is needed for ease of reading.</d:p>
      <d:p>The attribute <d:c>@part</d:c> is at the time of writing (July 2021) assumed by the
         schema but is not actively used in the mark-up.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="sourceDesc"
           corresp="row_sourceDesc">
      <d:p>When used in corpus.xml (<d:c>/teiCorpus/teiHeader/fileDesc/sourceDesc</d:c>),
            <d:c>sourceDesc</d:c> contains the project bibliography.</d:p>
      <d:p>When used in a transcription file header (<d:c>/TEI/teiHeader/fileDesc/sourceDesc</d:c>),
            <d:c>sourceDesc</d:c> contains details on the texts transcribed from the manuscript in
         question (<d:c>msContents</d:c>) and a physical description of the manuscript
            (<d:c>physDesc</d:c>).</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="listBibl"
           corresp="row_listBibl">
      <d:p>This element contains a bibliography. The type of works detailed in the bibliography is
         indicated via <d:c>@type</d:c>.</d:p>
      <d:p>The attribute <d:c>@default</d:c> is at the time of writing (July 2021) assumed by the
         schema but is not actively used in the mark-up.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="msDesc"
           corresp="row_msDesc">
      <d:p>This element contains details about a particular manuscript. It can be used to list a
         manuscript within the corpus bibliography in corpus.xml or in the transcription file header
         to describe the manuscript from which transcription has been made.</d:p>
      <d:p>The attribute <d:c>@status</d:c> is at the time of writing (July 2021) assumed by the
         schema but is not actively used in the mark-up.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="msIdentifier"
           corresp="row_msIdentifier">
      <d:p>This element contains identifying details about a manuscript. When used in the corpus
         bibliography in corpus.xml, the manuscript is assigned a unique ID via <d:c>@xml:id</d:c>.
         When used in transcription file headers, this ID is referenced via
         <d:c>@sameAs</d:c>.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="settlement"
           corresp="row_settlement">
      <d:p>Used within <d:c>msIdentifier</d:c>, this contains the location of the manuscript
         repository.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="repository"
           corresp="row_repository">
      <d:p>Used within <d:c>msIdentifier</d:c>, this contains the name of the manuscript
         repository.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="idno"
           corresp="row_idno">
      <d:p>Used within <d:c>msIdentifier</d:c>, this contains the manuscript's shelfmark.</d:p>
      <d:p>Used within <d:c>publicationStmt</d:c> in a transcription file header, this provides a
         publication ID for the transcription. This should be the same as the value of the
            <d:c>@xml:id</d:c> attribute of the ancestor <d:c>TEI</d:c>.</d:p>
      <d:p>This element is also used in some bibliography items (e.g.
            <d:c>/teiCorpus/teiHeader/fileDesc/sourceDesc/listBibl/biblStruct/monogr/idno</d:c>).</d:p>
      <d:p>How <d:c>idno</d:c> is being used is identified by <d:c>@type</d:c>.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="msName"
           corresp="row_msName">
      <d:p>This optional element within <d:c>msIdentifier</d:c> can be used to provide a name
         commonly in use for the manuscript being identified (e.g. 'The Yellow Book of Lecan' for
         Dublin, TCD H.2.16 (1318)).</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="history"
           corresp="row_history">
      <d:p>This provides information on a manuscript's history. When used within the corpus
         bibliography, it simply contains the manuscript's approximate date
            (<d:c>history/origin/date</d:c>). When used within a transcription file header, it
         contains narrative metadata describing the manuscript's history
            (<d:c>history/summary/p</d:c>).</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="origin"
           corresp="row_origin">
      <d:p>This is used within the corpus bibliography to provide the manuscript's approximate date
            (<d:c>history/origin/date</d:c>).</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="date"
           corresp="row_date">
      <d:p>When used in corpus.xml or in a transcription file header, this element provides a date
         for a manuscript(<d:c>history/origin/date</d:c>), bibliographical work
            (<d:c>listBibl/biblStruct/monogr/imprint/date</d:c>), or scribe
            (<d:c>profileDesc/handNotes/handNote</d:c>). For bibliographical works, this is a
         calendar year. For manuscripts and scribes, it is a century or pair of centuries.</d:p>
      <d:p>When used within a transcription, this element is used to mark up a date, but only when
         this date is in a format that cannot be analysed and marked up as words. For example,
         "1411" would be marked up with <d:c>date</d:c>, whereas "annaladh an tigerna ann so .i.
         mile bliadain cetra cead acus seacht bliadna acus tri .xx." ("the year of the Lord today,
         1467") would be marked up as normal transcribed text.</d:p>
      <d:p>In terms of the use of <d:c>date</d:c> to provide a date for a scribe, this can require
         particularly complex use of attributes:</d:p>
      <d:list>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@from</d:c> and <d:c>@to</d:c> indicate a precise span of years in which the
            scribe is known to have been active, where this information is available. If there is
            only evidence for them being active in a single year, then both attributes point to that
            year.</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@min</d:c> and <d:c>@max</d:c> are used to give a much broader estimate of the
            period in which the scribe was active and may be the only dating attributes used if not
            positive information about the scribe is available.</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@type</d:c> indicates what sort of span <d:c>@from</d:c> and <d:c>@to</d:c> /
               <d:c>@min</d:c> and <d:c>@max</d:c> relate to. Possible values include "floruit" and
            "lifespan".</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@cert</d:c> provides an editorial certainty level for the dating information
            contained in the rest of the element.</d:item>
      </d:list>
      <d:p>At the time of writing (July 2021), the dating information for scribal hands is in some
         disrepair and could use thorough checking in terms of data and standardisation in terms of
         encoding.</d:p>
      <d:p>Where <d:c>date</d:c> is used to provide the date of a manuscript, the century in which
         the manuscript was mainly created is indicated via <d:c>@from-custom</d:c>.</d:p>
      <d:p>All <d:c>date</d:c> elements require an <d:c>@id</d:c> attribute to be compliant with the
         DASG schema.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="biblStruct"
           corresp="row_biblStruct">
      <d:p>Appearing within the corpus bibliograhy, this element contains an individual bibliography
         item that is not a manuscript. In other words, it is the equivalent of
            <d:code>msDesc</d:code> for monographs, journal articles, book chapters, etc.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="monogr"
           corresp="row_monogr">
      <d:p>Appearing within the corpus bibliograhy, this contains details for either a monograph or
         the "top-level" component of a publication (e.g. the journal, in the context of a journal
         article). The "bottom-level" component is detailed under <d:c>analytic</d:c>.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="forename"
           corresp="row_forename">
      <d:p>In the corpus bibliography, this element is a child of <d:c>name</d:c> and contains the
         author or editor's first name.</d:p>
      <d:p>This element also appears as a direct child of <d:c>handNote</d:c>, containing the
         scribe's first name, where known.</d:p>
      <d:p>The attribute <d:c>@full</d:c> is at the time of writing (July 2021) assumed by the
         schema but is not actively used in the mark-up.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="surname"
           corresp="row_surname">
      <d:p>In the corpus bibliography, this element is a child of <d:c>name</d:c> and contains the
         author or editor's surname.</d:p>
      <d:p>This element also appears as a direct child of <d:c>handNote</d:c>, containing the
         scribe's surname, where known.</d:p>
      <d:p>The attribute <d:c>@full</d:c> is at the time of writing (July 2021) assumed by the
         schema but is not actively used in the mark-up.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="imprint"
           corresp="row_imprint">
      <d:p>This contains child elements providing information relating specifically to the
         publication of a bibliography item.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="pubPlace"
           corresp="row_pubPlace">
      <d:p>This identifies the bibliograhy item's place of publication.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="publisher"
           corresp="row_publisher">
      <d:p>This identifies the bibliograhy item's publisher.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="series"
           corresp="row_series">
      <d:p>This identifies the series of which a bibliograhy item is part, where applicable.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="biblScope"
           corresp="row_biblScope">
      <d:p>This element contains a number or range, which is the number of pages, volumes, etc.
         taken up by the bibliography item. The unit involved is indicated via
         <d:c>@unit</d:c>.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="analytic"
           corresp="row_analytic">
      <d:p>This element details the "bottom-level" component of a bibliography item (e.g. the
         article, as distinct from the journal, in an entry on a journal article); it is used
         alongside <d:c>monogr</d:c>, which details the "top-level" component.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="note"
           corresp="row_note">
      <d:p>This element is used in a variety of contexts.</d:p>
      <d:p>Within <d:c>teiHeader</d:c>, <d:c>note</d:c> contains text providing a free prose account
         of the aspect or datum indicated by an ancestor element. For example, <d:c>note</d:c>
         within <d:c>handNote</d:c> provides background information and a description of a
         particular scribe. In this context, depending on where <d:c>note</d:c> is used,
            <d:c>p</d:c> is sometimes required and sometimes not.</d:p>
      <d:p>Within transcriptions, <d:c>note</d:c> is used to insert a footnote. In these cases, it
         is identfied as such by <d:c>@type</d:c> and the editor responsible for the footnote is
         identified by <d:c>@resp</d:c>. In this context, the footnote must be contained within a
            <d:c>p</d:c> child element.</d:p>
      <d:p>The attribute <d:c>@anchored</d:c> is at the time of writing (July 2021) assumed by the
         schema but is not actively used in the mark-up.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="edition"
           corresp="row_edition">
      <d:p>This element identifies which edition of a bibliography item was used.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="encodingDesc"
           corresp="row_encodingDesc">
      <d:p>This contains a number of child elements detailing differnt aspects of how the source
         material is encoded in the file.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="projectDesc"
           corresp="row_projectDesc">
      <d:p>This element is only used in <d:c>teiHeader</d:c> in corpus.xml. It provides a brief
         overview of the FnaG MSS project.</d:p>
      <d:p>The attribute <d:c>@default</d:c> is at the time of writing (July 2021) assumed by the
         schema but is not actively used in the mark-up.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="samplingDecl"
           corresp="row_samplingDecl">
      <d:p>This element is only used in <d:c>teiHeader</d:c> in corpus.xml. It provides an
         explanation of how material was selected for transcription.</d:p>
      <d:p>The attribute <d:c>@default</d:c> is at the time of writing (July 2021) assumed by the
         schema but is not actively used in the mark-up.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="editorialDecl"
           corresp="row_editorialDecl">
      <d:p>This element is only used in <d:c>teiHeader</d:c> in corpus.xml. It contains a number of
         child elements detailing different editorial aspects of the project's transcription
         process.</d:p>
      <d:p>The attribute <d:c>@default</d:c> is at the time of writing (July 2021) assumed by the
         schema but is not actively used in the mark-up.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="correction"
           corresp="row_correction">
      <d:p>This element is only used in <d:c>teiHeader</d:c> in corpus.xml. It details the approach
         taken to emendations of source material on the project.</d:p>
      <d:p>The attribute <d:c>@default</d:c> is at the time of writing (July 2021) assumed by the
         schema but is not actively used in the mark-up.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="normalization"
           corresp="row_normalization">
      <d:p>This element is only used in <d:c>teiHeader</d:c> in corpus.xml. It details the approach
         taken to normalisation of spelling in source material on the project.</d:p>
      <d:p>The attributes <d:c>@default</d:c> and <d:c>@method</d:c> is at the time of writing (July
         2021) assumed by the schema but is not actively used in the mark-up.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="punctuation"
           corresp="row_punctuation">
      <d:p>This element is only used in <d:c>teiHeader</d:c> in corpus.xml. It details the approach
         taken to punctuation in source material and transcriptions on the project.</d:p>
      <d:p>The attribute <d:c>@default</d:c> is at the time of writing (July 2021) assumed by the
         schema but is not actively used in the mark-up.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="segmentation"
           corresp="row_segmentation">
      <d:p>This element is only used in <d:c>teiHeader</d:c> in corpus.xml. It details the approach
         taken to sub-dividing source material, from manuscript to word level, on the project.</d:p>
      <d:p>The attribute <d:c>@default</d:c> is at the time of writing (July 2021) assumed by the
         schema but is not actively used in the mark-up.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="hi"
           corresp="row_hi">
      <d:p>This element is used within editorial commentary (in <d:c>teiHeader</d:c> or in
         footnotes) to specify how a string of text is to be formatted in the output. This is done
         using <d:c>@rend</d:c>, which can use values like:</d:p>
      <d:list>
         <d:item>"italics"</d:item>
         <d:item>"bold"</d:item>
         <d:item>"sup" (superscript)</d:item>
      </d:list>
      <d:p>Note that this tag will not necessarily result in the output being formatted this way, as
         matching handling for <d:c>hi</d:c> will need to have been implemented in the appropriate
         stylesheet.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="classDecl"
           corresp="row_classDecl">
      <d:p>This provides a series of child elements detailing systems of IDs and attribute values in
         use across the corpus and definitions thereof.</d:p>
      <d:p>At the time of writing (July 2021), many of these are incomplete or require review.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="taxonomy"
           corresp="row_taxonomy">
      <d:p>Within <d:c>classDecl</d:c>, this element contains child elements that detail a
         particular category of IDs and attribute or element values in use in the corpus. The
         category is identified via <d:c>@xml:id</d:c>.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="gloss"
           corresp="row_gloss">
      <d:p>This element is contained by <d:c>taxonomy</d:c> and details an ID or attribute/element
         value in use across the corpus. The ID or attribute/element value is identified via
            <d:c>@xml:id</d:c> and the definition contained as text within <d:c>gloss</d:c>.</d:p>
      <d:p>Note that this element does <d:hi rend="italics">not</d:hi> have anything to do with
         editorial or scribal glossing of texts. The latter is marked up within transcriptions using
            <d:c>add</d:c>.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="charDecl"
           corresp="row_charDecl">
      <d:p>This element is only used in <d:c>teiHeader</d:c> in corpus.xml. It contains child
         elements detailing each abbreviation and ligature (<d:c>glyph</d:c>) used in the
         corpus.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="glyph"
           corresp="row_glyph">
      <d:p>This element contains details on a single abbreviation or ligature, as identified and
         classified by the project transcribers when encountered in the manuscript material.</d:p>
      <d:p>The abbreviation or ligature is assigned a unique ID via <d:c>@xml:id</d:c>;
         abbreviations' IDs are prefixed "g" and ligatures' IDs are prefixed "l". If it appears in
         the <d:ref target="https://www.vanhamel.nl/codecs/Show:Tionscadal_na_Nod">Tionscadal na
            Nod</d:ref> database, then a URL for its entry there is provided via
         <d:c>@corresp</d:c>.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="glyphName"
           corresp="row_glyphName">
      <d:p>This is the name of the abbreviation or ligature, as determined by the project
         transcribers.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="profileDesc"
           corresp="row_profileDesc">
      <d:p>In the <d:c>teiHeader</d:c> of corpus.xml, this element contains details of each of the
         scribes whose hands appear in the corpus</d:p>
      <d:p>In the <d:c>teiHeader</d:c> of each transcription file, this element contains details on
         the linguistic profile(s) of the text(s) transcribed, a list of scribal hands present in
         the portion(s) of the manuscript from which transcription was made, and a list of keywords
         describing the transcription as a whole.</d:p>
      <d:p>When it appears in <d:c>msItem</d:c>, this element is there to contain a list of keywords
         describing the individual text.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="handNotes"
           corresp="row_handNotes">
      <d:p>This element contains a set of <d:c>handNote</d:c> elements.</d:p>
      <d:p>In the <d:c>teiHeader</d:c> of corpus.xml, these in turn contain details on the
         scribes.</d:p>
      <d:p>In the <d:c>teiHeader</d:c> of a transcription file, these <d:c>handNote</d:c> elements
         are empty and merely point to the <d:c>handNote</d:c> elements in copus.xml via the
         latter's unique IDs.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="handNote"
           corresp="row_handNote">
      <d:p>This element contains child elements providing information about a scribe.</d:p>
      <d:p>In the <d:c>teiHeader</d:c> of corpus.xml, it contains details on the scribe, who is
         assigned a unique ID (prefixed "Hand") via <d:c>@xml:id</d:c>.</d:p>
      <d:p>In the <d:c>teiHeader</d:c> of a transcription file, these <d:c>handNote</d:c> elements
         are empty and merely point to the <d:c>handNote</d:c> elements in copus.xml via
            <d:c>@corresp</d:c>, which has as a value the scribe's unique ID.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="region"
           corresp="row_region">
      <d:p>This element appears within a <d:c>handNote</d:c> element in corpus.xml and details a
         region in which the scribe was known to be active. Multiple <d:c>region</d:c> elements can
         be identified if need be.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="affiliation"
           corresp="row_affiliation">
      <d:p>This identifies the social network to which the scribe belongs. A specific set of element
         values must be used, they must be spelt correctly, and only one <d:c>affiliation</d:c>
         element can be added to each <d:c>handNote</d:c>. A list of these values can be found at
            <d:c>taxonomy xml:id="social_group"</d:c> in corpus.xml. These strict rules are in place
         because this data determines the colour-coding of Gephi graphs and the program that
         generates these graphs is expecting particular text strings.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="revisionDesc"
           corresp="row_revisionDesc">
      <d:p>Appearing at the end of each <d:c>teiHeader</d:c>, this contains a changelog of changes
         made to the file.</d:p>
      <d:p>At the time of writing (July, 2021), the schema assumes that this element has the
         attribute <d:c>@status</d:c> with the value "draft". Also, transcribers have not hitherto
         kept these changelogs up to date, due to the frequency of changes made while preparing the
         corpus, sometimes to multiple files. These changelogs are therefore likely to be
         out-of-date and possibly inaccurate. Their continued presence should be reviewed.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="change"
           corresp="row_change">
      <d:p>This element describes a change made to the file. It has the following attributes:</d:p>
      <d:list>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@when</d:c>: the date of the change (yyy-mm-dd).</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@who</d:c>: the ID of the editor responsible.</d:item>
      </d:list>
      <d:p>At the time of writing (July, 2021), the schema assumes that this element has the
         attribute <d:c>@status</d:c> with the value "draft".</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="TEI"
           corresp="row_TEI">
      <d:p>This is the highest-level element and ultimate common ancestor of a transcription file.
         The transcription is assigned a unique ID via <d:c>@xml:id</d:c>
      </d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="extent"
           corresp="row_extent">
      <d:p>This indicates how many words are in the transcription ("{count(//w[not(ancestor::w)])}
         words").</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="notesStmt"
           corresp="row_notesStmt">
      <d:p>This provides a short summary that introduces the manuscript, briefly surveys the
         contents, and explains why it has been included in the FnaG MSS Corpus.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="msContents"
           corresp="row_msContents">
      <d:p>This contains one or more <d:c>msItem</d:c> elements, each of which details a text
         included in the transcription.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="summary"
           corresp="row_summary">
      <d:p>This introduces the texts transcribed from the manuscript, providing an overall summary
         of date, genre, subject-matter, authorship, and so forth, as well the reasons for
         transcribing them and an evaluation of what they contribute to the corpus.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="msItem"
           corresp="row_msItem">
      <d:p>This contains a series of child elements providing details on a single text transcription
         from the manuscript. The text is assigned a unique ID via <d:c>@xml:id</d:c>.</d:p>
      <d:p>Information specific to this text can be provided via a <d:c>note</d:c> child node.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="locus"
           corresp="row_locus">
      <d:p>This specifies the location of the text in the manuscript, usually in terms of start and
         end page/folio, column, and line.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="author"
           corresp="row_author">
      <d:p>Each of these elements identifies an author or scribe responsible for the text.</d:p>
      <d:p>The <d:c>@role</d:c> attribute identifies whether the individual in question is an
         "author" or a "scribe"; <d:c>@corresp</d:c> has as its value the individual's unique
         ID.</d:p>
      <d:p>There is currently no system for formally documenting authors. This is perhaps because
         relatively few texts in the corpus have a confirmed author; almost all texts that do are
         likely to be poetry. For this reason, there are currently no <d:c>author</d:c> elements
         where <d:c>@type</d:c> has the value "author" and there are no unique IDs specified for
         authors.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="incipit"
           corresp="row_incipit">
      <d:p>This contains the first few words of the text, as transcribed. If the text appears to be
         acephalous, this should be indicated with [...] and the first transcribed words added
         thereafter.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="explicit"
           corresp="row_explicit">
      <d:p>This contains the last few words of the text, as transcribed. If the ending appears to be
         missing, this should be indicated with [...] and the last transcribed words added
         thereafter.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="filiation"
           corresp="row_filiation">
      <d:p>This element can be used to provide details on other versions of the text and this
         version's relationship thereto.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="textLang"
           corresp="row_textLang">
      <d:p>This element identifies the main language used in the text, via <d:c>@mainLang</d:c>. If
         there are other languages that have a significant influence, these can be detailed in a
         whitespace-separated list as the value of <d:c>@otherLangs</d:c>.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="biblFull"
           corresp="row_biblFull">
      <d:p>Within <d:c>msItem</d:c>, this element is only used to ultimately contain a keyword list
         for the text; the only TEI-compliant way to add such a list at text-level is to create a
         bibliography item for it via this element.</d:p>
      <d:p>At the time of writing (July, 2021), the schema assumes that this element has the
         attributes <d:c>@status</d:c> and <d:c>@default</d:c>.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="textClass"
           corresp="row_textClass">
      <d:p>
         <d:c>textClass</d:c>, in <d:c>msItem</d:c>, contains a keyword list relating to the
         text.</d:p>
      <d:p>At the time of writing (July, 2021), the schema assumes that this element has the
         attribute <d:c>@default</d:c>.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="keywords"
           corresp="row_keywords">
      <d:c>keywords</d:c> in <d:c>msItem</d:c>
      contains a set of keywords relating to the text.</d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="term"
           corresp="row_term">
      <d:p>
         <d:c>term</d:c>
      </d:p> in <d:c>msItem</d:c>
      contains a keyword that has been used to help classify the text.</d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="ref"
           corresp="row_ref">
      <d:p>This element appears in editorial commentary (header material and footnotes). It is used
         to mark up a reference to another source and provide, where possible, an ID for that source
            (<d:c>@target</d:c>). The type of source is indicated via <d:c>@type</d:c>.</d:p>
      <d:p>There is currently (July 2021) no output for material from the corpus that makes use of
         data from the <d:c>ref</d:c> tag or its attributes and it is not used consistently. It
         should be decided whether it can be used, for example, to automatically generate content
         for popin windows that would provide bibliographical details or whether the tag should be
         retired and all referencing done via the in-text author-date references only.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="physDesc"
           corresp="row_physDesc">
      <d:p>This element contains a description of physical aspects of the manuscript from which
         transcription has been made. This is done in general via direct child <d:c>p</d:c> nodes
         and <d:c>objectDesc</d:c> and <d:c>handDesc</d:c>.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="objectDesc"
           corresp="row_objectDesc">
      <d:p>
         <d:c>objectDesc</d:c> provides details specifically about the physical state and
         appearance of the mauscript page.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="supportDesc"
           corresp="row_supportDesc">
      <d:p>
         <d:c>supportDesc</d:c> provides details specifically about the physical state of the
         mauscript page.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="support"
           corresp="row_support">
      <d:p>
         <d:c>support</d:c> contains a brief formal description of the typical writing surface in
         the manuscript.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="foliation"
           corresp="row_foliation">
      <d:p>
         <d:c>foliation</d:c> indicates whether the foliation is modern, scribal, or post-scribal,
         or if multiple systems are in use.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="condition"
           corresp="row_condition">
      <d:p>
         <d:c>condition</d:c>
      </d:p> describes the
      overall condition of the manuscript.</d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="layoutDesc"
           corresp="row_layoutDesc">
      <d:p>
         <d:c>layout</d:c>
      </d:p> provides a
      brief description of the typical layout of the manuscript page.</d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="langUsage"
           corresp="row_langUsage">
      <d:p>This element provides more detailed information on the language(s) used in the material
         transcribed from the manuscript to which the file relates.</d:p>
      <d:p>At the time of writing (July, 2021), the schema assumes that this element has the
         attribute <d:c>@default</d:c>.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="text"
           corresp="row_text">
      <d:p>This element represents a text within the corpus represented <d:c>teiCorpus</d:c>; it
         contains all transcribed material in the file.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="body"
           corresp="row_body">
      <d:p>This element contains all transcribed material in the file.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="div"
           corresp="row_div">
      <d:p>Where <d:c>div</d:c> has no ancestor <d:c>div</d:c>, it represents a text within a
         transcription, although some transcriptions consist of a single text. It is linked to the
         details about the text in <d:c>msItem</d:c> via <d:c>@corresp</d:c> using the text's unique
         ID.</d:p>
      <d:p>Where <d:c>div</d:c> has an ancestor <d:c>div</d:c>, it represents a subdivision of a
         text. This is used when the text is prose but consists of clearly identifiable units (e.g.
         a collection of medical aphorisms). This subdivision is assigned a unique ID via
            <d:c>@xml:id</d:c>.</d:p>
      <d:p>In both cases, the text/subdivision are described with the followign information via
         attributes:</d:p>
      <d:list>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@n</d:c>: this is the number assigned to the text/subdivision; it is not a
            unique ID but will display on screen to indicate where the text is in the transcription
            in certain sorts of output.</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@type</d:c>: this identifies whether the text is "prose", "verse", or
            "divprose" (subdivided prose); if it is a subdivision of prose text, the value will be
            "prosediv".</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@hand</d:c>: this identifies the main scribe responsible for the text; if
            multiple scribes are involved, it identifies the first major scribal
            contributor.</d:item>
      </d:list>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="handShift"
           corresp="row_handShift">
      <d:p>This element is placed wherever a new scribe begins writing, whether this is at the
         beginning of the transcription, where they take over mid-text, or where they make an
         addition to the text. At least one <d:c>handShift</d:c> element must appear at the start of
         the transcription but, if the scribe does not change thereafter, it is not necessary to add
         any more. The new scribe is indicated via <d:c>@new</d:c> using their unique ID.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="pb"
           corresp="row_pb">
      <d:p>This element indicates the start of transcription from a new page.</d:p>
      <d:p>It uses the following elements:</d:p>
      <d:list>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@n</d:c>: This is the number of the new page, based on the conventional
            foliation of the manuscript; it need not be a unique ID but it will appear to designate
            the new page in some outputs.</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@xml:id</d:c>: This is a unique ID for the new page.</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@facs</d:c>: This provides a URL for an online image of the new page, where
            available; it must be a link directly to the image, not to a page that contains the
            image.</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@sameAs</d:c>: Where the new page begins in the middle of a word that requires
            editorial emendation, the <d:c>pb</d:c> element must be provided twice; as it cannot be
            given two <d:c>@xml:id</d:c> attributes with the same value, as there can only be one
               <d:c>@xml:id</d:c> with a given value in a document, <d:c>@sameAs</d:c> must be used
            in any other instances of the <d:c>pb</d:c>.</d:item>
      </d:list>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="lb"
           corresp="row_lb">
      <d:p>This element indicates the start of transcription from a new line.</d:p>
      <d:p>It uses the following elements:</d:p>
      <d:list>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@n</d:c>: This is the number of the new line; it need not be a unique ID but
            it will appear to designate the new line in some outputs.</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@xml:id</d:c>: This is a unique ID for the new line.</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@sameAs</d:c>: Where the new line begins in the middle of a word that requires
            editorial emendation, the <d:c>lb</d:c> element must be provided twice; as it cannot be
            given two <d:c>@xml:id</d:c> attributes with the same value, as there can only be one
               <d:c>@xml:id</d:c> with a given value in a document, <d:c>@sameAs</d:c> must be used
            in any other instances of the <d:c>lb</d:c>.</d:item>
      </d:list>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="w"
           corresp="row_w">
      <d:p>
         <d:c>w</d:c> can be used to mark up a transcribed word within a transcription. In the
         case of compound words, it is used to mark up both the "lower-level" individual component
         words and the "upper-level" containing word. Alternatively, in hwData.xml, it appears
         within <d:c>entryFree</d:c> providing lexical data on a headword from the corpus.</d:p>
      <d:p>When used to mark up a transcribed word (whether "lower-level" or "upper-level"), it can
         have the following attributes:</d:p>
      <d:list>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@lemma</d:c>: this indicates the headword of which the transcribed word has
            been identified as a form. If the word cannot be identified with a headword in the form
            in which it appears, the value of <d:c>@lemma</d:c> is "UNKNOWN".</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@source</d:c>: if the headword has been postulated based on another headword,
            the postulated headword is provided via <d:c>@lemma</d:c> (prefixed with *) and the
            nearest identified headword provided via <d:c>@source</d:c>; the URL for the
               <d:c>@source</d:c> headword is provided via <d:c>@lemmaRef</d:c>.</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@lemmaRef</d:c>: this provides a URL for the dictionary entry for the headword
            (where available) in a recognised dictionary (in order of preference, eDIL, Dwelly via
            Faclair Beag, Teanglann, placename databases). Where the URL is from Dwelly via Faclair
            Beag, hwData.xml should be checked to see if the headword is already present and the URL
            from hwData used instead of the new URL that Faclair Beag will offer.</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@lemmaSL</d:c>: when the transcribed word is the subject of an HDSG slip, this
            attribute provides the HDSG version of the headword from the slip.</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@slipRef</d:c>: when the transcribed word is the subject of an HDSG slip, this
            attribute provides the URL for the HDSG slip in the DASG database.</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@pos</d:c>: this details the word's part of speech.</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@xml:lang</d:c>: if the word is not in some form of Gaelic, the language is
            specified via this attribute using its XML language code. In such cases, no attributes
            other than <d:c>@id</d:c> (see below).</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@corresp</d:c>: When a transcribed word is not found in any recognised
            dictionary, is documented in an HDSG slip, but not in an HDSG slip that relates to the
            particular transcribed word in question, the URL for the slip in the DASG database is
            referenced via <d:c>@corresp</d:c>.</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@lemmaDW</d:c>: If the Scottish Gaelic headword to which an eDIL headword is
            linked in hwData.xml is not the correct Scottish Gaelic headword to which to link the
            transcribed word, the transcribed word can be linked to a Dwelly headword via this
            attribute.</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@lemmaRefDW</d:c>: If the Scottish Gaelic headword to which an eDIL headword
            is linked in hwData.xml is not the correct Scottish Gaelic headword to which to link the
            transcribed word, the transcribed word can be linked to an URL for the correct Dwelly
            headword via this attribute. hwData.xml should be checked to see if the Dwelly headword
            is already present and the URL from hwData used instead of the new URL that Faclair Beag
            will offer.</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@lemmaTG</d:c>: Where an Irish headword from Teanglann is also of relevance,
            this can be referenced via this attribute.</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@lemmaRefTG</d:c>: Where an Irish headword from Teanglann is also of
            relevance, its URL can be provided via this attribute.</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@function</d:c>: In T10, words have been linked via <d:c>@function</d:c> to an
            XML file which provides different readings for these words in previous transcriptions.
            This is not handled in any output from the corpus and it should be reviewed whether this
            attribute is still needed.</d:item>
      </d:list>
      <d:p>None of these attributes except <d:c>@id</d:c> (see below) is compulsory and should not
         be included unless the information can be securely associated with the transcribed
         word.</d:p>
      <d:p>When used to provide information on a headword in hwData.xml, it can have the following
         attributes:</d:p>
      <d:list>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@type</d:c>: Uses of the <d:c>w</d:c> element in hwData are distinguished from
               <d:c>w</d:c> elsewhere via <d:c>@type="data"</d:c>.</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@lemma</d:c>: This provides the first instance of the headword linked to the
               <d:c>@lemmaRef</d:c> encountered in the corpus.</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@lemmaRef</d:c>: This is the unique ID for the headword entry in
            hwData.</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@pos</d:c>: This provides the <d:c>@pos</d:c> value from the first instance of
            the headword linked to the <d:c>@lemmaRef</d:c> encountered in the corpus.</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@lemmaDW</d:c>: If the headword is from eDIL, the equivalent headword from
            Dwelly can be provided here.</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@lemmaDW</d:c>: If the headword is from eDIL, the equivalent headword from
            Dwelly can be identified via its Faclair Beag URL using this attribute.</d:item>
      </d:list>
      <d:p>In all circumstances, <d:c>w</d:c> requires a unique <d:c>@id</d:c> in order to be
         compliant with the DASG schema.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="abbr"
           corresp="row_abbr">
      <d:p>This is used to enclose all transcribed characters involved in an abbreviation or
         ligature. The direct text children of this element are characters that have been written
         plene; the characters in the <d:c>g</d:c> element(s) are the expansion of one or more
         abbreviations placed on those characters. Alternatively, the abbreviation could be
         freestanding, meaning there is only one or more <d:c>g</d:c>elements; all ligatures are
         freestanding.</d:p>
      <d:p>
         <d:c>@cert</d:c> identifies the certainty with which the transcriber has expanded the
         abbreviation. <d:c>@cert="unknown"</d:c> is used when the transcription is not being made
         from the manuscript itself but from another modern transcription, where text has been
         formatted as an abbreviation expansion but no information has been provided on the
         abbreviation; it means that the transcriber is aware that an abbreviation is used here but
         cannot comment on the certainty of its expansion as they have no direct access to it.</d:p>
      <d:p>When the abbreviation has been placed on one word but the expansion belongs in the
         preceding or following word, or where the expanion straddles a word boundary, <d:c>g</d:c>
         elements are placed where needed to place letters in the words to which they belong. They
         are then all linked to each other and their parent <d:c>abbr</d:c> using a unique ID via
            <d:c>@corresp</d:c>.</d:p>
      <d:p>An <d:c>abbr</d:c> element can be nested within another <d:c>abbr</d:c> element, for
         example, if there is one abbreviation whose expansion is confinsed to the word on which it
         is placed and one whose expansion straddles a word boundary placed on the same letter.
         Nested <d:c>abbr</d:c> elements can also be used to distinguish two expansions with
         significantly different certainty levels.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="g"
           corresp="row_g">
      <d:p>This element contains characters expanded from an abbreviation or ligature. The
         abbreviation or ligature is identified via its unique ID using <d:c>@ref</d:c>.</d:p>
      <d:p>When the abbreviation has been placed on one word but the expansion belongs in the
         preceding or following word, or where the expanion straddles a word boundary, <d:c>g</d:c>
         elements are placed where needed to place letters in the words to which they belong. They
         are then all linked to each other and their parent <d:c>abbr</d:c> using a unique ID via
            <d:c>@corresp</d:c>.</d:p>
      <d:p>In all circumstances, <d:c>g</d:c> requires a unique <d:c>@id</d:c> in order to be
         compliant with the DASG schema.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="space"
           corresp="row_space">
      <d:p>This element represents a space left by the scribe between words within a manuscript
         line.</d:p>
      <d:p>Its attribute, <d:c>@type</d:c>, can have one of several values:</d:p>
      <d:list>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@scribal</d:c>: this means that the space is an ordinary space for this
            scribe.</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@em</d:c>: this means that the space is approximately three times as large as
            a standard space for this scribe.</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@force</d:c>: this will create a space in the "Semi-Diplomatic" edition on
            Meanma where a space would not otherwise be added according to the standard rules that
            Meanma applies.</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@editorial</d:c>: this is used when the text is not being transcribed from a
            manuscript but from another modern transcription where word division has been
            standardised; it means that the transcriber does not know whether the scribe is
            responsible for this space, but the space is there in their source.</d:item>
      </d:list>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="pc"
           corresp="row_pc">
      <d:p>This element contains scribal punctuation.</d:p>
      <d:p>In all circumstances, <d:c>pc</d:c> requires a unique <d:c>@id</d:c> in order to be
         compliant with the DASG schema.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="add"
           corresp="row_add">
      <d:p>This element contains a later scribal addition to the main text, whether by the main
         scribe of the text or another hand.</d:p>
      <d:p>It can have the following attributes:</d:p>
      <d:list>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@type</d:c>: this determines whether the addition is an "insertion" or a
            "gloss".</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@hand</d:c>: this identifies the hand responsible for the addition via its
            unique ID. Note that, if a different scribe is making the addition compared to that
            writing the main text, <d:c>handShift</d:c> should still be used within <d:c>add</d:c>
            alongside <d:c>@hand</d:c>. Note also that the resumption of the first hand should be
            indicated via <d:c>handShift</d:c> after <d:c>add</d:c>.</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@place</d:c>: This identifies the location on the page where the insertion has
            been written (e.g. "above" [the line], "below" [the line], "margin, top").</d:item>
      </d:list>
      <d:p>Note that this element should <d:hi rend="bold">not</d:hi> be used to make an editorial
         addition to the transcription; that is done via <d:c>supplied</d:c>.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="del"
           corresp="row_del">
      <d:p>This element marks up text deleted by a scribe, either by the scribe that wrote it or by
         another.</d:p>
      <d:p>Note that this element should <d:hi rend="bold">not</d:hi> be used to make an editorial
         deletion from the transcription; that is done via <d:c>choice</d:c>.</d:p>
      <d:p>The scribe responsible for the deletion is identified, where possible, via
            <d:c>@hand</d:c> using their unique ID.</d:p>
      <d:p>At the time of writing (July, 2021), the schema assumes that this element has the
         attributes <d:c>@status</d:c> and <d:c>@instant</d:c>.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="supplied"
           corresp="row_supplied">
      <d:p>A transcriber can use <d:c>supplied</d:c> to add characters or words to a transcription,
         if it is thought that these have been omitted purely in error or if their absence risks
         causing serious confusion. The member of the project team responsible is identified via
            <d:c>@resp</d:c> using their unique ID.</d:p>
      <d:p>At the time of writing (July, 2021), the schema assumes that this element has the
         attribute <d:c>@instant</d:c>.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="seg"
           corresp="row_seg">
      <d:p>
         <d:c>seg</d:c> has various purposes within a transcription. How it is being used is
         determined by <d:c>@type</d:c>. The most common values, which are handled on Meanma, are
         "cfe" (<d:hi rend="italics">ceann fo eite</d:hi>), "fragment" (characters from a word that
         is partly obliterated and cannot be reconstructed), and "catchword". "title" and "margNote"
         (with <d:c>@xml:id</d:c>) are in use but not currently handled on Meanma; their use should
         be reviewed.</d:p>
      <d:p>Where <d:c>@type="fragment"</d:c>, <d:c>seg</d:c> requires a unique <d:c>@id</d:c> in
         order to be compliant with the DASG schema.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="unclear"
           corresp="row_unclear">
      <d:p>This element is used to mark up text that the transcriber judges to be unclear.</d:p>
      <d:p>Why the text is being marked up is indicated via <d:c>@reason</d:c>:</d:p>
      <d:list>
         <d:item>"text_obscure": the writing is difficult to make out due to erosion, smudging, or
            unconventional ductus.</d:item>
         <d:item>"damage": the writing surface is completely gone, with no chance of the original
            text being recovered; the transcriber has been able to postulate what was written there,
            however. This is thus editorially equivalent to <d:c>supplied</d:c>. The difference is
            that <d:c>supplied</d:c> contains material that was possibly never present in the text
            but is thought to be needed anyway, whereas <d:c>unclear reason="damage"</d:c>
            postulates a reading for a span of text that probably was once physically
            present.</d:item>
         <d:item>"fold": the writing is obscured by the way the page is arranged in the digital
            image, in a way that is unlikely to be a problem if the manuscript were to be examined
            in person.</d:item>
         <d:item>"interp_obscure": the writing is perfectly legible but the words cannot be tagged
            with confidence.</d:item>
      </d:list>
      <d:p>The certainty with which the transcriber has provided the text in <d:c>unclear</d:c> is
         indicated via <d:c>@cert</d:c>. The transcriber responsible is identified via
            <d:c>@resp</d:c>.</d:p>
      <d:p>At the time of writing (July, 2021), the schema assumes that this element has the
         attribute <d:c>@instant</d:c>.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="lg"
           corresp="row_lg">
      <d:p>This element contains the metrical lines that make up a stanza, whether determined by
         metrical analysis or scribal layout. It should always be the direct child of
         <d:c>div</d:c>, whether the stanzas constitute an indepdent verse text in the manuscript or
         are embedded within a prose text.</d:p>
      <d:p>The following attributes are used:</d:p>
      <d:list>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@n</d:c>: This is the stanza number; it is not a unique ID but it will be
            displayed in most outputs.</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@type</d:c>: This should always be set to "stanza".</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@xml:id</d:c>: This is a unique ID for the stanza.</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@sameAs</d:c>: At the time of writing (July, 2021), in one instance, this is
            used to link a couplet placed elsewhere in the poem to the stanza to which it is thought
            to belong. This usage should be reviwed, as it is the only example and it may not be
            handled in any outputs.</d:item>
      </d:list>
      <d:p>At the time of writing (July, 2021), the schema assumes that this element has the
         attributes <d:c>@org</d:c>, <d:c>@sample</d:c>, and <d:c>@part</d:c>.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="l"
           corresp="row_l">
      <d:p>This element represents a metrical line within a stanza (<d:c>lg</d:c>).</d:p>
      <d:p>The following attributes are used:</d:p>
      <d:list>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@n</d:c>: This is the line letter; it is not a unique ID but it will be
            displayed in most outputs.</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@xml:id</d:c>: This is a unique ID for the metrical line.</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@sameAs</d:c>: At the time of writing (July, 2021), in one instance, this is
            used to link a couplet placed elsewhere in the poem to the stanza to which it is thought
            to belong. This usage should be reviwed, as it is the only example and it may not be
            handled in any outputs.</d:item>
      </d:list>
      <d:p>At the time of writing (July, 2021), the schema assumes that this element has the
         attribute <d:c>@part</d:c>.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="choice"
           corresp="row_choice">
      <d:p>This element contains an emendation made to the text by one of the FnaG MSS project
         transcribers.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="sic"
           corresp="row_sic">
      <d:p>Appearing within an emendation (<d:c>choice</d:c>), this element contains the original
         reading from the manuscript.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="corr"
           corresp="row_corr">
      <d:p>Appearing within an emendation (<d:c>choice</d:c>), this element contains the
         transcriber's amended reading. If the emendation is to delete the manuscript reading, then
            <d:c>corr</d:c> should be left empty.</d:p>
      <d:p>The transcriber is identified using their unique ID via <d:c>@resp</d:c>.</d:p>
      <d:p>At the time of writing (July, 2021), the schema assumes that this element has the
         attribute <d:c>@instant</d:c>.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="c"
           corresp="row_c">
      <d:p>This element is used to mark up one or more transcribed characters that cannot be
         assigned to a marked up word, date, or number. This is usually because the rest of the word
         is unclear but it can also be because a scribe simply added a single character without
         meaning it to be grouped with anything else.</d:p>
      <d:p>
         <d:c>c</d:c> and <d:c>seg type="fragment"</d:c> play essentially the same editorial role.
            <d:c>seg type="fragment"</d:c> was introduced because the TEI Guidelines do not permit
         the use of <d:c>abbr</d:c> within <d:c>c</d:c> and some "fragments" in the transcriptions
         contain expandable abbreviations. Going forwards, it could well be possible to mark up all
         fragments as <d:c>seg type="fragment"</d:c> and use <d:c>c</d:c> only to mark up
         intentionally solitary characters.</d:p>
      <d:p>In all circumstances, <d:c>c</d:c> requires a unique <d:c>@id</d:c> in order to be
         compliant with the DASG schema.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="gap"
           corresp="row_gap">
      <d:p>
         <d:c>gap</d:c> indicates that material from the text once appeared, or should appear, at
         this point but cannot be transcribed. It is always empty as, by definition, there is
         nothing to transcribe.</d:p>
      <d:p> The reason for the <d:c>gap</d:c>, which often resembles that for <d:c>unclear</d:c>, is
         indicated via <d:c>reason</d:c> e.g.: </d:p>
      <d:list>
         <d:item>"text_obscure": the writing is illegible due to erosion, smudging, or
            unconventional ductus.</d:item>
         <d:item>"damage": the writing surface is completely gone, with no chance of the original
            text being recovered and the transcriber has not been able to postulate what was written
            there.</d:item>
         <d:item>"fold": the writing is obscured by the way the page is arranged in the digital
            image, in a way that is unlikely to be a problem if the manuscript were to be examined
            in person.</d:item>
         <d:item>"text_omitted": there is no physical problem with the manuscript but analysis of
            the syntax or sense or comparison with other versions of the text implies that material
            has been omitted.</d:item>
         <d:item>"loss_of_folios": the text is missing its beginning or end or contains a chasm due
            to the loss of one or more entire folios from the manuscript.</d:item>
      </d:list>
      <d:p>Various other reasons are in use in addition to the above at the time of writing (July,
         2021). Not all of the reasons currently in use are handled on Meanma, which can lead to no
         information being returned for a <d:c>gap</d:c>. The reasons in use in this context should
         be reviewed and streamlined and proper handling developed for what remains.</d:p>
      <d:p>What other attributes are used depend on what is known about the gap.</d:p>
      <d:p>If an estimate can be made of how long the gap is, the following are included:</d:p>
      <d:list>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@unit</d:c>: the unit of measurement being used to estimate the gap (e.g.
            "chars", "words", "folios".</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@quantity</d:c>: the length of the gap in the specified unit (e.g. "3", where
               <d:c>@unit="chars"</d:c>, to indicate that the gap allows space for three
            characters).</d:item>
      </d:list>
      <d:p>If the length of the gap is unknown (common where <d:c>@reason="text_omitted"</d:c>),
         this is indicated by instead using <d:c>@extent</d:c> with the value "unknown".</d:p>
      <d:p>In all instances, the editor responsible for attempting to estimate the gap is indicated
         via <d:c>@resp</d:c> using their unique ID. Furthermore, <d:c>c</d:c> requires a unique
            <d:c>@id</d:c> in order to be compliant with the DASG schema.</d:p>
      <d:p>At the time of writing (July, 2021), the schema assumes that this element has the
         attribute <d:c>@instant</d:c>.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="cb"
           corresp="row_cb">
      <d:p>This element indicates the start of transcription from a new column.</d:p>
      <d:p>It uses the following elements:</d:p>
      <d:list>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@n</d:c>: This is the letter of the new column; it need not be a unique ID but
            it will appear to designate the new column in some outputs.</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@xml:id</d:c>: This is a unique ID for the new column.</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@sameAs</d:c>: Where the new column begins in the middle of a word that
            requires editorial emendation, the <d:c>cb</d:c> element must be provided twice; as it
            cannot be given two <d:c>@xml:id</d:c> attributes with the same value, as there can only
            be one <d:c>@xml:id</d:c> with a given value in a document, <d:c>@sameAs</d:c> must be
            used in any other instances of the <d:c>cb</d:c>.</d:item>
      </d:list>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="head"
           corresp="row_head">
      <d:p>This element contains a title (<d:c>title</d:c>) for a transcribed text or subdivision
         thereof. At the time of writing (July, 2021), however, it is used inconsistently, sometimes
         containing a purely editorial title and sometimes containing a title that is part of the
         transcribed text. This should be reviewed and standardised; alternatively, the two usages
         should be distinguished via an attribute.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="anchor"
           corresp="row_anchor">
      <d:p>This element is currently (July, 2021) used only once, where a folio of one manuscript in
         the corpus (MS9) is physically part of another manuscript (MS7). This folio comprises part
         of a larger text, the rest of which is still present in MS9 (MS9.7). The contents of the
         folio have been transcribed as a text within Transcription 7 (MS7.7) and an
            <d:c>anchor</d:c> placed at its location within the larger text in MS9. It is linked to
         the larger text via the <d:c>@copyOf</d:c> and <d:c>@source</d:c> attributes and its role
         is identified via <d:c>@type</d:c> ("crossRef").</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="list"
           corresp="row_list">
      <d:p>This element is used in hwData.xml to present lists of headwords either added or removed
         from the corpus since hwData.xml was last generated.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="item"
           corresp="row_item">
      <d:p>This element is used within <d:c>list</d:c> in hwData.xml to present a headword either
         added or removed from the corpus since hwData.xml was last generated.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="entryFree"
           corresp="row_entryFree">
      <d:p>This element represents an entry in the hwData.xml database. It contains a record for a
         single headword from the corpus.</d:p>
      <d:p>It has the following attributes:</d:p>
      <d:list>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@corresp</d:c> has as its value the URL for the headword (its unique
            identifier).</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@n</d:c> has as its value the number of times this headword occurs in the
            corpus.</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@source:</d:c> is added to new <d:c>entryFree</d:c> elements when they are
            added to the database, with the value set to "new". Once the transcriber adding the
            headword data has finished with the entry, this attribute is removed. It can be retained
            if the entry needs further attention and will be retained automatically if present when
            the database is re-generated.</d:item>
      </d:list>
      <d:p>At the time of writing (July, 2021), the schema assumes that this element has the
         attributes <d:c>@type</d:c> and <d:c>@opt</d:c>.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="span"
           corresp="row_span">
      <d:p>This element appears within <d:c>w</d:c> in hwData.xml. It is used to present both the
         headword itself (or the different versions thereof, if headwords have been postulated based
         on the URL) and forms of the headword(s) that occurs in the corpus.</d:p>
      <d:p>It uses two attributes:</d:p>
      <d:list>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@type</d:c>: this determines if it is a headword ("lem") or a "form".</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@n</d:c>: this presents the number of times this headword or form appears in
            the corpus.</d:item>
      </d:list>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="gen"
           corresp="row_gen">
      <d:p>This element appears within <d:c>w</d:c> in hwData.xml. It indicates the gender of the
         headword ("m", "f", or "n"), where applicable, as given in whichever recognised
         dictionaries are being drawn on for this headword.</d:p>
      <d:p>The linguistic period during which this is the headword's gender is indicated via
            <d:c>@xml:lang</d:c> using XML language codes. If the gender changes between periods,
         multiple <d:c>gen</d:c> elements are used. If a word can have different genders within the
         same linguistic period, these are distinguished from each other and linked to their
         accompanying stem (<d:c>iType</d:c>) using <d:c>@n</d:c>. If the gender remains the same
         from a given linguistic period onwards, it is the current convention to not list subsequent
         periods unless the stem changes.</d:p>
      <d:p>At the time of writing (July, 2021), the schema assumes that this element has the
         attribute <d:c>@opt</d:c>.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="iType"
           corresp="row_iType">
      <d:p>This element appears within <d:c>w</d:c> in hwData.xml. It indicates the declensional
         stem of the headword, where applicable, as given in eDIL.</d:p>
      <d:p>The linguistic period during which this is the headword's stem is indicated via
            <d:c>@xml:lang</d:c> using XML language codes. If the stem changes between periods,
         multiple <d:c>iType</d:c> elements are used. If a word can have different declensions
         within the same linguistic period, these are distinguished from each other and linked to
         their accompanying gender (<d:c>gen</d:c>) using <d:c>@n</d:c>. If the declensional stem
         remains the same from a given linguistic period onwards, it is the current convention to
         not list subsequent periods unless the gender changes.</d:p>
      <d:p>At the time of writing (July, 2021), the schema assumes that this element has the
         attribute <d:c>@opt</d:c>.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
           element="gramGrp"
           corresp="row_gramGrp">
      <d:p>This element is used in a hwData.xml entry when the word be used in different
         parts-of-speech and have different genders and declensional stems depending on how it is
         used. The POS is identified via <d:c>@type</d:c>. Currently, this is only needed for nouns
         and adjectives.</d:p>
      <d:p>At the time of writing (July, 2021), the schema assumes that this element has the
         attribute <d:c>@opt</d:c>.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
</d:descs>
