<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<d:descs
   xmlns="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml"
   xmlns:d="https://github.com/conmaol/faclair-manuscripts/blob/master/Transcribing/Data/TEI%20Structure/teiStructure_descs.xml">
   <d:desc element="teiCorpus" corresp="row_teiCorpus">
      <d:p>This element encloses the entire corpus and is the common ancestor of all other
         elements.</d:p>
      <d:p>XPath: /*</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc element="teiHeader" corresp="row_teiHeader">
      <d:p>This element contains metadata about a TEI file. Where used in corpus.xml, it contains
         data referenced by <d:c>@xml:id</d:c> from across the rest of the corpus. It includes names
         and other details of scribes and abbreviations, for example.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc element="fileDesc" corresp="row_fileDesc">
      <d:p>When a direct child of <d:c>teiHeader</d:c>, <d:c>fileDesc</d:c> contains bibliographical
         information about the file itself. It is also used within <d:c>msItem/biblFull</d:c> to
         contain a keyword list relating to the individual text; this latter structure is mostly
         unnecessary for the purposes of the corpus but is required for TEI conformance.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc element="titleStmt" corresp="row_titleStmt">
      <d:p>This contains the most basic bibliographical information about the work to which it
         relates, namely, the title and optionally details of anyone responsible.</d:p>
      <d:p>Where its parent is <d:c>teiHeader/fileDesc</d:c>, it provides details for the entire TEI
         file. When that file is corpus.xml, it contains the corpus title and a list of those who
         have worked on the corpus in various capacities. Where that file is a transcription file,
         it provides a title for the transcription and names the editor primarily responsible for
         that transcription, although it is likely that it has been reviewed by multiple team
         members in reality.</d:p>
      <d:p>Where its parent is <d:c>biblFull/fileDesc</d:c> (i.e. it relates to an individual text),
         it provides the title for that text.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc element="title" corresp="row_title">
      <d:p>This is used in a variety of contexts to contain the title of a file, bibliographical
         work, or a transcribed text within the corpus or a subsection thereof.</d:p>
      <d:p>Even where the <d:c>title</d:c> element appears within a transcription (e.g.
            <d:c>TEI/text/body/div/head/title</d:c>), it remains part of the editorial apparatus. In
         other words, the <d:c>title</d:c> element is never used to mark up titles that appear in
         manuscripts. For avoidance of doubt, the <d:c>title</d:c> element is also never used for a
         person's title.</d:p>
      <d:list>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@level</d:c> is only used in the context of a bibliography entry; it is used to
            differentiate a monograph title from the title of a multi-authored book in which the
            work being described appears, for example.</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@type</d:c> is also only used in the context of a bibliography entry, where it
            distinguishes a condensed version of a work's title from the full version.</d:item>
      </d:list>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc element="respStmt" corresp="row_respStmt">
      <d:p>The <d:c>respStmt</d:c> element contains other elements detailing one or more
         individuals' responsibility for a file or bibliographical work.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc element="name" corresp="row_name">
      <d:p>The <d:c>name</d:c> element is used in a variety of contexts to contain an anthroponym,
         toponym, demonym, or other sort of name.</d:p>
      <d:p>Where it appears within <cdoe>respStmt</cdoe>, it contains the name of an individual
         responsible for a file or bibliographical work. In this context, the name is split into
            <d:c>forename</d:c> and <d:c>surname</d:c>.</d:p>
      <d:p>Where it appears within a transcription (<d:c>text//name</d:c>), it is used to mark up
         the occurrence of a name in a transcription. In this context, it must contain at least one
            <d:c>w</d:c> element and could contain any of the markup used for transcribed text (e.g.
         unclear, space). If part or all of the name requires emendation, the <d:c>choice</d:c>
         element must be contained within <d:c>name</d:c> and not contain it. <d:c>name</d:c> can
         also contain a nested <d:c>name</d:c> element, where one <d:c>name</d:c> contains another
            <d:c>name</d:c> (e.g. Mael Coluim).</d:p>
      <d:p>The following attributes are in active use with <d:c>name</d:c>:</d:p>
      <d:list>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@id</d:c>: all <d:c>name</d:c> elements require this attribute to be compliant with
            the DASG schema.</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@xml:id</d:c>: when names of project members are given in <d:c>respStmt</d:c>
            elements in corpus.xml, they are assigned unique IDs via this attribute there. These IDS
            can be used to reference them elsewhere, usually using <d:c>@resp</d:c>.</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@type</d:c>: when the <d:c>name</d:c> element is used to mark up a name in a
            transcription, this identifies what sort of name it is (e.g. personal, place).</d:item>
         <d:item>
            <d:c>@corresp</d:c>: when the <d:c>name</d:c> element is used to mark up a placename in
            a transcription, this attribute can be used to link to an entry for that name in an
            external placenames database (e.g. logainm.ie) via an URL. It can be used whether or not
            the word(s) in the name have also been linked to headwords and the same URL can be used
            here and for a contained word's <d:c>@lemmaRef</d:c>.</d:item>
      </d:list>
      <d:p>Other attributes (<d:c>@full</d:c>, <d:c>@instant</d:c>) are at the time of writing (July
         2021) assumed by the schema but are not actively used in the mark-up.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc element="resp" corresp="row_resp">
      <d:p>
         <d:c>resp</d:c> is used within respStmt to describe a responsibility belonging to the
         person named in the sibling <d:c>name</d:c> element.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc element="publicationStmt" corresp="row_publicationStmt">
      <d:p>When used in the <d:code>fileDesc</d:code> element relating to a TEI file, this element
         contains information relating to the publication of the file and its contents, such as who
         is responsbile for it and any restrictions on its use.</d:p>
      <d:p>When used in the <d:code>fileDesc</d:code> element relating to a text item from a
         transcription (<d:code>msItem/biblFull/fileDesc/publicationStmt</d:code>), this element
         simply contains the statement that the item is a "Draft transcription"; publication is
         already provided by the <d:code>publicationStmt</d:code> at file level.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc element="authority" corresp="row_authority">
      <d:p><d:c>authority</d:c> refers to the body responsible for the file and its
         publication.</d:p>
      <d:p>In corpus.xml, this element contains the contact details for the Faclair na Gàidhlig
         project and is identified with the <d:c>@xml:id</d:c> "authority". Elsewhere, this element
         links to these details via <d:c>@sameAs="authority"</d:c>.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc element="address" corresp="row_address">
      <d:p>This contains contact details for the Faclair na Gàidhlig project, comprised of a series
            <d:c>addrLine</d:c> elements.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc element="addrLine" corresp="row_addrLine">
      <d:p>This contains a line of the street address for the Faclair na Gàidhlig project.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc element="email" corresp="row_email">
      <d:p>This contains an email address for the Faclair na Gàidhlig project.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc element="num" corresp="row_num">
      <d:p>The meaning of this element varies depending on context.</d:p>
      <d:p>When it appears within <d:c>addrLine</d:c>, it contains a telephone number for the
         Faclair na Gàidhlig project.</d:p>
      <d:p>When it appears within a transcription, it is used to mark up a number that cannot be
         tagged as a single word and link to a dictionary headword or where the number appears in a
         manuscript as apparatus rather than in a syntactic context.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc element="availability" corresp="row_availability">
      <d:p>This contains information on how the file can be used. This is set to "restricted" via
            <d:c>status</d:c> and contains the following (within <d:c>p</d:c>): "For internal use by
         the Faclair na Gàidhlig/DASG projects." </d:p>
      <d:p>The attribute <d:c>@default</d:c> is at the time of writing (July 2021) assumed by the
         schema but is not actively used in the mark-up.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc element="p" corresp="row_p">
      <d:p><d:c>p</d:c> is a very widely used element. It is used to contain text belonging in a
         single paragraph.</d:p>
      <d:p>In corpus.xml and in the <d:c>teiHeader</d:c> of transcription files and the hwData file,
         it is used to organise prose metadata added by editors.</d:p>
      <d:p>Within transcriptions (<d:c>text//p</d:c>), it is used to contain transcribed prose. A
         new <d:c>p</d:c> element is begun when the text switches back from verse to prose, when the
         scribe visually indicates a major new subdivision of a prose text, or if the editors feel a
         new paragraph is needed for ease of reading.</d:p>
      <d:p>The attribute <d:c>@part</d:c> is at the time of writing (July 2021) assumed by the
         schema but is not actively used in the mark-up.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc element="sourceDesc" corresp="row_sourceDesc">
      <d:p>When used in corpus.xml (<d:c>/teiCorpus/teiHeader/fileDesc/sourceDesc</d:c>),
            <d:c>sourceDesc</d:c> contains the project bibliography.</d:p>
      <d:p>When used in a transcription file header (<d:c>/TEI/teiHeader/fileDesc/sourceDesc</d:c>),
            <d:c>sourceDesc</d:c> contains details on the texts transcribed from the manuscript in
         question (<d:c>msContents</d:c>) and a physical description of the manuscript
            (<d:c>physDesc</d:c>).</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc element="listBibl" corresp="row_listBibl">
      <d:p>This element contains a bibliography. The type of works detailed in the bibliography is
         indicated via <d:c>@type</d:c>.</d:p>
      <d:p>The attribute <d:c>@default</d:c> is at the time of writing (July 2021) assumed by the
         schema but is not actively used in the mark-up.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc element="msDesc" corresp="row_msDesc">
      <d:p>This element contains details about a particular manuscript. It can be used to list a
         manuscript within the corpus bibliography in corpus.xml or in the transcription file header
         to describe the manuscript from which transcription has been made.</d:p>
      <d:p>The attribute <d:c>@status</d:c> is at the time of writing (July 2021) assumed by the
         schema but is not actively used in the mark-up.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc element="msIdentifier" corresp="row_msIdentifier">
      <d:p>This element contains identifying details about a manuscript. When used in the corpus
         bibliography in corpus.xml, the manuscript is assigned a unique ID via <d:c>@xml:id</d:c>.
         When used in transcription file headers, this ID is referenced via
         <d:c>@sameAs</d:c>.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc element="settlement" corresp="row_settlement">
      <d:p>Used within <d:c>msIdentifier</d:c>, this contains the location of the manuscript
         repository.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc element="repository" corresp="row_repository">
      <d:p>Used within <d:c>msIdentifier</d:c>, this contains the name of the manuscript
         repository.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc element="idno" corresp="row_idno">
      <d:p>Used within <d:c>msIdentifier</d:c>, this contains the manuscript's shelfmark.</d:p>
      <d:p>Used within <d:c>publicationStmt</d:c> in a transcription file header, this provides a
         publication ID for the transcription. This should be the same as the value of the
            <d:c>@xml:id</d:c> attribute of the ancestor <d:c>TEI</d:c>.</d:p>
      <d:p>How <d:c>idno</d:c> is being used is identified by <d:c>@type</d:c>.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc element="msName" corresp="row_msName">
      <d:p>This optional element within <d:c>msIdentifier</d:c> can be used to provide a name
         commonly in use for the manuscript being identified (e.g. 'The Yellow Book of Lecan' for
         Dublin, TCD H.2.16 (1318)).</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc element="history" corresp="row_history">
      <d:p>This provides information on a manuscript's history. When used within the corpus
         bibliography, it simply contains the manuscript's approximate date
            (<d:c>history/origin/date</d:c>). When used within a transcription file header, it
         contains narrative metadata describing the manuscript's history
            (<d:c>history/summary/p</d:c>).</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc element="origin" corresp="row_origin">
      <d:p>This is used within the corpus bibliography to provide the manuscript's approximate date
            (<d:c>history/origin/date</d:c>).</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc element="date" corresp="row_date">
      <d:p>When used in corpus.xml or in a transcription file header, this element provides a date
         for a manuscript(<d:c>history/origin/date</d:c>), bibliographical work
            (<d:c>listBibl/biblStruct/monogr/imprint/date</d:c>), or scribe
            (<d:c>profileDesc/handNotes/handNote</d:c>). For bibliographical works, this is a
         calendar year. For manuscripts and scribes, it is a century or pair of centuries.</d:p>
      <d:p>When used within a transcription, this element is used to mark up a date, but only when
         this date is in a format that cannot be analysed and marked up as words. For example,
         "1411" would be marked up with <d:c>date</d:c>, whereas "annaladh an tigerna ann so .i.
         mile bliadain cetra cead acus seacht bliadna acus tri .xx." ("the year of the Lord today,
         1467") would be marked up as normal transcribed text.</d:p>
      <d:p>In terms of the use of <d:c>date</d:c> to provide a date for a scribe, this can require
         particularly complex use of attributes:</d:p>
      <d:list>
         <d:item><d:c>@from</d:c> and <d:c>@to</d:c> indicate a precise span of years in which the
            scribe is known to have been active, where this information is available. If there is
            only evidence for them being active in a single year, then both attributes point to that
            year.</d:item>
         <d:item><d:c>@min</d:c> and <d:c>@max</d:c> are used to give a much broader estimate of the
            period in which the scribe was active and may be the only dating attributes used if not
            positive information about the scribe is available.</d:item>
         <d:item><d:c>@type</d:c> indicates what sort of span <d:c>@from</d:c> and <d:c>@to</d:c> /
               <d:c>@min</d:c> and <d:c>@max</d:c> relate to. Possible values include "floruit" and
            "lifespan".</d:item>
         <d:item><d:c>@cert</d:c> provides an editorial certainty level for the dating information
            contained in the rest of the element.</d:item>
      </d:list>
      <d:p>At the time of writing (July 2021), the dating information for scribal hands is in some
         disrepair and could use thorough checking in terms of data and standardisation in terms of
         encoding.</d:p>
      <d:p>Where <d:c>date</d:c> is used to provide the date of a manuscript, the century in which
         the manuscript was mainly created is indicated via <d:c>@from-custom</d:c>.</d:p>
      <d:p>All <d:c>date</d:c> elements require an <d:c>@id</d:c> attribute to be compliant with the
         DASG schema.</d:p>
   </d:desc>
   <d:desc element="biblStruct" corresp="row_biblStruct"/>
   <d:desc element="monogr" corresp="row_monogr"/>
   <d:desc element="forename" corresp="row_forename"/>
   <d:desc element="surname" corresp="row_surname"/>
   <d:desc element="imprint" corresp="row_imprint"/>
   <d:desc element="pubPlace" corresp="row_pubPlace"/>
   <d:desc element="publisher" corresp="row_publisher"/>
   <d:desc element="series" corresp="row_series"/>
   <d:desc element="biblScope" corresp="row_biblScope"/>
   <d:desc element="analytic" corresp="row_analytic"/>
   <d:desc element="note" corresp="row_note"/>
   <d:desc element="edition" corresp="row_edition"/>
   <d:desc element="encodingDesc" corresp="row_encodingDesc"/>
   <d:desc element="projectDesc" corresp="row_projectDesc"/>
   <d:desc element="samplingDecl" corresp="row_samplingDecl"/>
   <d:desc element="editorialDecl" corresp="row_editorialDecl"/>
   <d:desc element="correction" corresp="row_correction"/>
   <d:desc element="normalization" corresp="row_normalization"/>
   <d:desc element="punctuation" corresp="row_punctuation"/>
   <d:desc element="segmentation" corresp="row_segmentation"/>
   <d:desc element="hi" corresp="row_hi"/>
   <d:desc element="classDecl" corresp="row_classDecl"/>
   <d:desc element="taxonomy" corresp="row_taxonomy"/>
   <d:desc element="gloss" corresp="row_gloss"/>
   <d:desc element="charDecl" corresp="row_charDecl"/>
   <d:desc element="glyph" corresp="row_glyph"/>
   <d:desc element="glyphName" corresp="row_glyphName"/>
   <d:desc element="profileDesc" corresp="row_profileDesc"/>
   <d:desc element="handNotes" corresp="row_handNotes"/>
   <d:desc element="handNote" corresp="row_handNote"/>
   <d:desc element="region" corresp="row_region"/>
   <d:desc element="affiliation" corresp="row_affiliation"/>
   <d:desc element="ref" corresp="row_ref"/>
   <d:desc element="revisionDesc" corresp="row_revisionDesc"/>
   <d:desc element="change" corresp="row_change"/>
   <d:desc element="TEI" corresp="row_TEI"/>
   <d:desc element="extent" corresp="row_extent"/>
   <d:desc element="notesStmt" corresp="row_notesStmt"/>
   <d:desc element="msContents" corresp="row_msContents"/>
   <d:desc element="summary" corresp="row_summary"/>
   <d:desc element="msItem" corresp="row_msItem"/>
   <d:desc element="locus" corresp="row_locus"/>
   <d:desc element="author" corresp="row_author"/>
   <d:desc element="incipit" corresp="row_incipit"/>
   <d:desc element="explicit" corresp="row_explicit"/>
   <d:desc element="filiation" corresp="row_filiation"/>
   <d:desc element="textLang" corresp="row_textLang"/>
   <d:desc element="biblFull" corresp="row_biblFull"/>
   <d:desc element="textClass" corresp="row_textClass"/>
   <d:desc element="keywords" corresp="row_keywords"/>
   <d:desc element="term" corresp="row_term"/>
   <d:desc element="physDesc" corresp="row_physDesc"/>
   <d:desc element="objectDesc" corresp="row_objectDesc"/>
   <d:desc element="supportDesc" corresp="row_supportDesc"/>
   <d:desc element="support" corresp="row_support"/>
   <d:desc element="foliation" corresp="row_foliation"/>
   <d:desc element="condition" corresp="row_condition"/>
   <d:desc element="layoutDesc" corresp="row_layoutDesc"/>
   <d:desc element="langUsage" corresp="row_langUsage"/>
   <d:desc element="text" corresp="row_text"/>
   <d:desc element="body" corresp="row_body"/>
   <d:desc element="div" corresp="row_div"/>
   <d:desc element="handShift" corresp="row_handShift"/>
   <d:desc element="pb" corresp="row_pb"/>
   <d:desc element="lb" corresp="row_lb"/>
   <d:desc element="w" corresp="row_w"/>
   <d:desc element="abbr" corresp="row_abbr"/>
   <d:desc element="g" corresp="row_g"/>
   <d:desc element="space" corresp="row_space"/>
   <d:desc element="pc" corresp="row_pc"/>
   <d:desc element="add" corresp="row_add"/>
   <d:desc element="del" corresp="row_del"/>
   <d:desc element="supplied" corresp="row_supplied"/>
   <d:desc element="seg" corresp="row_seg"/>
   <d:desc element="unclear" corresp="row_unclear"/>
   <d:desc element="lg" corresp="row_lg"/>
   <d:desc element="l" corresp="row_l"/>
   <d:desc element="choice" corresp="row_choice"/>
   <d:desc element="sic" corresp="row_sic"/>
   <d:desc element="corr" corresp="row_corr"/>
   <d:desc element="c" corresp="row_c"/>
   <d:desc element="gap" corresp="row_gap"/>
   <d:desc element="provenance" corresp="row_provenance"/>
   <d:desc element="cb" corresp="row_cb"/>
   <d:desc element="head" corresp="row_head"/>
   <d:desc element="handDesc" corresp="row_handDesc"/>
   <d:desc element="anchor" corresp="row_anchor"/>
   <d:desc element="mod" corresp="row_mod"/>
   <d:desc element="list" corresp="row_list"/>
   <d:desc element="item" corresp="row_item"/>
   <d:desc element="entryFree" corresp="row_entryFree"/>
   <d:desc element="span" corresp="row_span"/>
   <d:desc element="gen" corresp="row_gen"/>
   <d:desc element="iType" corresp="row_iType"/>
   <d:desc element="gramGrp" corresp="row_gramGrp"/>
</d:descs>
