<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../Schemas/fnag_mss2.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../Coding/Stylesheets/basic-info.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="T8">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Transcription 8: A Gaelic Fragment in The Kingis Quair Manuscript (Oxford, Bodleian Library MS. Arch. Selden B.24)</title>
				<respStmt corresp="EPT">
					<name>Eystein P. Thanisch</name>
					<resp>Transcriber</resp>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt corresp="WGI">
					<name>William Gillies</name>
					<resp>Overseer</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<extent>24 words </extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority sameAs="authority"/>
				<availability sameAs="availability" status="restricted">
					<licence/>
				</availability>
				<idno>T8</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note>
					<p>The sole manuscript of <hi rend="italics">The Kingis Quare</hi> and <hi
							rend="italics">The Quare of Jealous</hi>, <ref type="ms" target="MS8"
							>Oxford, Bodleian Library MS. Arch. Selden B.24</ref>, which was
						produced sometime during the reign of James IV (1488–1513; Boffey &amp;
						Edwards <ref type="bib" target="Boffey1997">1997</ref>: 22) and which is
						also an important early witness to the works of Geoffrey Chaucer (d. 1400)
						and John Lydate (c. 1370–1451), contains a fragment of a Gaelic <hi
							rend="italics">dán díreach</hi> quatrain. This has been inscribed by
						Domhnall Gorm, presumably a MacDonald of Sleat, and may be celebrating his
						relationship with a member of the Lothian-based Sinclair family, who
						commissioned and owned the manuscript, by lamenting his parting from the.
						Its fragmentary condition inhibits confident interpretation, however.</p>
				</note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier sameAs="MS8">
						<settlement>Oxford</settlement>
						<repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
						<idno type="shelfmark">Arch. Selden B.24</idno>
					</msIdentifier>
					<msContents>
						<summary>
							<p>The only Gaelic material in the manuscript is Domhnall Gorm's
								quatrain, now lacunose.</p>
						</summary>
						<msItem n="1" xml:id="MS8.1" resp="Hand21">
							<locus>fol.231v4–6</locus>
							<title>Gaelic Verse Fragment</title>
							<incipit>[...] air cioth na coinne ...</incipit>
							<explicit>... air clar na cruinne</explicit>
							<note>
								<p comment="Content">This single quatrain in <hi rend="italics"
										>rannaigecht beag</hi> is not only lacking in context but is
									also missing two syllables each from lines a and c. As a result,
									its interpretation is difficult. The best attempt is a text and
									translation by William MacKenzie, with the assistance of William
									Watson (MacKenzie <ref type="bib" target="MacKenzie1939"
										>1939</ref>: 137), who acknowledges that their reading is
									uncertain. Their translation is as follows: <quote><l>… (from
											the tears) of the meeting,</l><l>now that the world has
											sped its leafage</l><l>… (bank) close to a
											pool,</l><l>(that?) we have found on the surface of the
											round world.</l><l>I (am) Donald
									Gorm</l></quote></p><p>In this reading the quatrain is
									celebrating some sort of fellowship or friendship, now gone. Its
									passing is compared to the fall of leaves in autumn. The
									friendship is compared to, or exemplified by, a scene on the
									banks of a pool. This intimate image is contrasted with its
									context in the vastness of the world, which presumably now
									separates the friends. The quatrain is followed by the
									signature, "misi dom<hi rend="italics">h</hi>nall gorm",
									Domhnall Gorm being a popular name among the chiefs of the
									MacDonalds of Sleat. If the inscription was made to celebrate
									the friendship of a Domhnall Gorm of Sleat and Lord Sinclair, or
									a relative, then this is most apposite.</p>
								<p>There are, however, two major problems with this translation.
									First, <hi rend="italics">cioth</hi> can mean "shower",
									"abundance", or "struggle" but "tears" is an apparently
									otherwise unattested poetic extension. Secondly, "<hi
										rend="italics">air</hi> buain" as the perfect form of <hi
										rend="italics">búainid</hi> would be a striking
									vernacularism in a formal and still early poem; it should surely
									be taken as a preposition (either <hi rend="italics">íar</hi> or
										<hi rend="italics">ar</hi>) and a verbal noun. and the
									subject need not be "biot<hi rend="italics">h</hi>".
									Furthermore, "na coin<hi rend="italics">n</hi>e" need not be
									analysed as art. + noun; "na" could also be <hi rend="italics">i
											<hi rend="sup">n-</hi></hi> + poss. 3rd sing. fem.,
									forming the phrase "against her/it", possibly referring to <hi
										rend="italics">bith</hi> on the next line.</p>
								<p>A resulting alternative translation, with most of the changes in
									the first couplet, would be:<quote><l>...to struggle against
											it,</l><l>against the world, to reap its
											foliage;</l><l>...{on the} bank, close to a
											pool</l><l>that we found on the surface of the round
											world.</l><l>I am Domhnall Gorm.</l></quote></p><p>Other
									intepretations are surely possible. For the purposes of the
									present text and discussion, Mackenzie/Watson's reading will be
									followed, except for the substitution in of a more context
									sensitive interpretation of "<hi rend="italics">air</hi>
									buain".</p>
								<p>A text was also attempted by J. T. T. Brown, with a translation
									from Rev. Robert Blair (Brown <ref target="Brown1899" type="bib"
										>1899</ref>: 151). However, Brown's transcription is so
									inaccurate that this is best left unconsidered.</p>
								<p comment="Style">The metre is <hi rend="italics">rannaigecht
										beag</hi> (7<hi rend="sup">2</hi>7<hi rend="sup">2</hi>7<hi
										rend="sup">2</hi>7<hi rend="sup">2</hi>). All metrical rules
									are observed, as far as is visible. The tone is elegaic and
									lyrical, although, as noted above, its stance is still open to
									interpretation.</p>
								<p comment="Social Context and Intended Readers">The quatrain is
									thought to have been inscribed during the 16<hi rend="sup"
										>th</hi> century. The manuscript was produced sometime after
									1489 and a note mentioning the date 1592 appears below the
									quatrain on fol. 231<hi rend="sup">v</hi>. While the quatrain
									could be later than this note, it is more likely to be
									contemporary or earlier (Black, <ref type="bib"
										target="Black2017">2017</ref>: §127). This is also the
									period when multiple individuals named Domhnall Gorm, or
									thereabouts, were chiefs of the MacDonalds of Sleat and when the
									manuscript was still owned by the Sinclair family. Domhnall Gorm
									Mór (d. 1616) was in Edinburgh, as a prisoner, in 1589
									(MacDonald &amp; MacDonald <ref target="MacDonald1904"
										type="bib">1904</ref>: 34–35). Brown also identifies him as
									the Domhnall Gorm in question (Brown <ref target="Brown1899"
										type="bib">1899</ref>: 146). It is perhaps too fanciful to
									imagine him borrowing the Sinclair's copy of <hi rend="italics"
										>The Kingis Quair</hi>, itself written in the persona of a
									high-status prisoner, and inscribing the present text in
									gratitude and as his own reflection. Suffice to say, given the
									provenance and ownership of the manuscript and the likely status
									of Domhnall Gorm, this poem should be understood as courtly
									communication between aristocrats. Thus it joins other pieces of
									evidence for Classical Gaelic literacy among the late medieval
									Scottish Gaelic nobility (see also Black <ref type="bib"
										>1978</ref>; Gillies <ref type="bib">Autumn 1978</ref>;
									Gillies <ref type="bib">Summer 1982</ref>). Indeed, it even
									implies an interest in Gaelic literature among the nobility far
									outside the core Gaelic world of the time.</p>
								<p comment="Studies and Editions">The only useable text and
									translation of the quatrain is that by MacKenzie (<ref
										type="bib" target="MacKenzie1939">1939</ref>: 137). There is
									also the superseded attempt by Brown (Brown <ref
										target="Brown1899" type="bib">1899</ref>: 151). The
									manuscript is available in facsimile (Boffey &amp; Edwards:
									1997).</p>
							</note>
							<filiation>
								<p>There are no other known manuscript versions of this quatrain,
									nor any known context from which it might have come.</p>
							</filiation>
							<textLang mainLang="ghc">
								<note comment="Orthography and Scribal Practices"><p>Given the
										shortness, ambiguity, and lacunose nature of the text, the
										linguistic observations that can be made about it are
										naturally limited.</p><p><list>
											<head>Orthography</head>
											<item>Long "í" is consistently "io".</item>
											<item>The preposition <hi rend="italics">ar</hi>
												(sometimes for <hi rend="italics">for</hi>) is
												consistently rendered "air"; this variant has
												existed throughout the history of Gaelic (eDIL <ref
												target="eDIL2013" type="bib">2013</ref>: s.v. 1
												ar).</item>
											<item>Lenition is marked where it would be expected to
												occur via a punctus over the consonant.</item>
											<item>There are no instances where the marking of
												eclipsis would be expected.</item>
											<item>Length marks are not used at all.</item>
											<item>"{b}ruaic<hi rend="italics">h</hi>" is used,
												whereas the internal rhyme (: "fu<hi rend="italics"
												>air</hi>") requires "{b}ruaig<hi rend="italics"
												>h</hi>" (<ref type="text_ed_line"
												target="MS8.1.1c">q1c</ref>).</item>
											<item>The later, slenderised nominative singular form of
												<hi rend="italics">lám</hi>, "laim" (<ref
												type="text_ed_line" target="MS8.1.1c">q1c</ref>),
												is used.</item>
										</list><list>
											<head>Scribal Practices</head>
											<item>Letter forms are standard Gaelic minuscule; the
												hand has a tendency to elongate some strokes
												relative to other hands. For example, the topmost
												horizontal stroke of his "s" and "f" stretches some
												distance over the character to the right.</item>
											<item>His "a" is composed of a particularly elaborate
												four-strokes, like a square balanced on one of its
												corners.</item>
											<item>Serifs are well-pronounced.</item>
											<item>Each couplet of the quatrain is written on a
												single manuscript line.</item>
											<item>Each line of the couplet is separated by a
												punctus.</item>
											<item>Word division is largely maintained, although
												prepositions and possessives are placed in closer
												proximity to their nouns.</item>
											<item>Contractions and abbreviations are standard and
												minimal; there are no generic suspensions standing
												for lengthy strings of letters, for example.</item>
											<item>Capitals, if used at all, are not clearly
												distinguished, even in the signature.</item>
										</list></p></note><note comment="Language">
									<p comment="Nominal System">
										<list>
											<item>Nouns are nominatives or genitives, with one
												possible occurence of a dative "{b}ruaic<hi
												rend="italics">h</hi>" (<ref type="text_ed_line"
												target="MS8.1.1c">q1c</ref>).</item>
											<item>An accusative ought to occur (re lin<hi
												rend="italics">n</hi>e (<ref target="MS8.1.1c"
												type="text_ed_line">q1c</ref>)) but, as it is at
												the end of a clause metrical line, there is no
												opportunity to observe the mutations it triggers.
												The form itself could equally be an accusative or a
												dative.</item>
											<item>No adjectives occur in this fragment.</item>
										</list></p><p comment="Verbal System">
										<list>
											<item>There is only one verb in the fragment: "fu<hi
												rend="italics">air</hi>" (<ref target="MS8.1.1d"
												type="text_ed_line">q1d</ref>), from <hi
												rend="italics">fo-gaib</hi>. Given the lack of an
												object in the following line, it appears to be be a
												relative, although neither an analytic ending nor a
												particle is used to indicate this. Alternatively, it
												could be a simple verb, with the object appearing in
												the previous line for metrical reasons.</item>
											<item>There is also a verbal noun: "buain" (<ref
												target="MS8.1.1b" type="text_ed_line">q1b</ref>).
												Its usage could be interpreted a variety of ways. It
												seems likely that, in conjunction with the preceding
												preposition "<hi rend="italics">air</hi>", is
												playing either a quasi-infinitival role ("with the
												intention of harvesting") or the role of a past
												participle ("after harvesting").</item>
										</list></p><p comment="Pronouns and Pronominals"><list>
											<item>Only one pronoun appears in the fragment: the
												emphatic "sin<hi rend="italics">n</hi>e" (<ref
												type="text_ed_line" target="MS8.1.1d">q1d</ref>).
												This appears to be the subject (or possibly the
												object) of "fu<hi rend="italics">air</hi>".</item>
										</list></p><p comment="Syntax"><list>
											<item>Given the lack of visible main verbs, the quatrain
												appers to be either a long single sentence
												comprising a series of prepositional phrases and
												relative clauses or merely a series of detached
												phrases.</item>
											<item>A number of genitival phrases also appear (e.g.
												"clar na cruin<hi rend="italics">n</hi>e" (<ref
												type="text_ed_line" target="MS8.1.1d"
												>q1d</ref>)).</item>
											<item>There is one possible accusative ("re lin<hi
												rend="italics">n</hi>e" (<ref type="text_ed_line"
												target="MS8.1.1c">q1c</ref>)), although whether it
												is being treated as such cannot be
												determined.</item>
											<item>No adverbials are used.</item>
										</list></p><p comment="Lexis"><list>
											<item>The fragment is dominated by images of nature,
												with a distinctly pastoral feel.</item>
											<item>The vocabulary used seems to be fairly standard
												and approachable to one conversant in Classical
												Gaelic poetry.</item>
											<item>Without more context, it is difficult to tell
												whether the language meant to be literal or
												allusive.</item>
											<item>There is one possible piece of technical
												vocabulary: "coin<hi rend="italics">n</hi>e" (<ref
												target="MS8.1.1a" type="text_ed_line">q1a</ref>).
												This has a range of more general meanings —
												"company", "meeting", "against" (with prep. <hi
												rend="italics">i <hi rend="sup">n-</hi></hi>) —
												but also the specific legal sense of free billeting
												(often anglicised in an Irish context as <hi
												rend="italics">coigny</hi>. There is no particular
												reason to suspect that it is being used in this
												sense in the present fragment but the ambiguous
												context leaves the possibility open.</item>
											<item>There are no loanwords in the fragment.</item>
										</list></p><p comment="Conclusions"><list>
											<item>Not enough of the quatrain has been preserved to
												allow definite conclusions as to the linguistic
												register but the well-observed formal bardic metre
												suggests that this is to be taken as Classical
												Gaelic poetry. Such a conclusion is also reached by
												MacKenzie/Watson (MacKenzie <ref type="bib"
												target="MacKenzie1939">1939</ref>: 137).</item>
											<item>One possible instance of Scottish dialectal
												influence is "{b}ruaic<hi rend="italics">h</hi>" for
												"{b}ruaig<hi rend="italics">h</hi>" (<ref
												type="text_ed_line" target="MS8.1.1c">q1c</ref>),
												against the need for a rhyme with "fu<hi
												rend="italics">air</hi>" (<ref type="text_ed_line"
												target="MS8.1.1d">q1d</ref>), possibly showing
												Scottish devoicing of /ɣ'/ to /χ'/.</item>
											<item>The verbal form, "fu<hi rend="italics">air</hi>
												si<hi rend="italics">n</hi>e" (<ref
												type="ed_text_line" target="MS8.1.1d">q1d</ref>),
												if it is to be taken as a relative, may also show
												vernacular influence, since it lacks both a particle
												and a verb ending. However, neither is it Scottish
												Gaelic <hi rend="italics">a fhuair</hi> and, given
												the lack of context, other interpretations are
												possible.</item>
										</list></p></note><note comment="Style"><p>As noted, the
										context of the fragment, both in terms of the rest of the
										quatrain and more widely, is lacking, meaning its use of
										language is difficult to interpret. It appears to be lyrical
										and elegaic, employing several images of nature or of
										pastoral scenes, possibly to describe the transience of
										things. This is all presented in a formal bardic metre and
										Classical language. It appears to be in the 1st person
										plural ("si<hi rend="italics">n</hi>e" (<ref
											type="ed_text_line" target="MS8.1.1d">q1d</ref>)),
										suggesting some sort of authorial presence, reinforced by
										the following signature. This implies that it is meant to be
										some sort of direct communication, although, from what
										survives, it appears to communicate largely by synechdochic
										allusion. The vocabulary is relatively mainstream, however,
										and there are no overt literary references to legendary
										people or places — although something may have been crammed
										into the lost four syllables — making the quatrain
										relatively approachable to anyone aware of the context but
										not necessarily highly learned in Gaelic tradition. All this
										reinforces the theory that this is a courtly communication
										between aristocrats, most likely a Domhnall Gorm of Sleat
										and a member of the Sinclair family.</p></note>
							</textLang>
							<biblFull>
								<fileDesc>
									<titleStmt>
										<title>Gaelic Verse Fragment</title>
									</titleStmt>
									<publicationStmt><p>Draft transcription</p></publicationStmt>
									<sourceDesc><p>Transcribed from manuscript</p></sourceDesc>
								</fileDesc>
								<profileDesc>
									<textClass>
										<keywords>	
											<term>misc</term>
											<term>bardic</term>
											<term>poetry</term>
											<term>personal</term>
										</keywords>
									</textClass>
								</profileDesc>
							</biblFull>
						</msItem>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support><p>Paper; 27 × 18.42cm (Hunt <ref target="Hunt1895"
											type="bib">1895</ref>: vol. 2:1, 614)</p></support>
								<foliation><p>Foliation is modern</p></foliation>
								<condition><p>Fol. 231<hi rend="sup">v</hi> is badly eroded in
										places, leading to the loss of the first two syllables of
										lines a and c in the quatrain under discussion, as well as
										some text immediately above that may have offered context.
										The facsimile by Boffey et al. (1997) includes photographs
										taken under UV light, which unfortunately do not offer much
										improvement. However, the parts of the quatrain that have
										escaped erosion are very clear and present no
									problems.</p></condition>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<p>The quatrain is one of a number of notes, including several Scots
									verses, written in a single broad column in the centre of fol.
										231<hi rend="sup">v</hi>. The quatrain itself is set out one
									couplet to a manuscript line.</p>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
						<handDesc>
							<handNote corresp="Hand21">
								<note comment="The Scribe">
									<p>The hand that produced the quatrain is identifiable as
										Domhnall Gorm only by the signature. This was a popular name
										among the MacDonalds of Sleat during the 16<hi rend="sup"
											>th</hi> and early 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> centuries so
										it is presumed to be one of this clan's chiefs. Interest in
										poetry on the part of the clan's senior members is attested
										in the next century through their patronage of Cathal Mac
										Mhuirich (Black <ref type="bib" target="Black1976-78"
											>1976–78</ref>: 332–339). Domhnall Gorm Mór seems to be
										the leading candidate due to him being known to have visited
										Edinburgh on several occasions (MacDonald &amp; MacDonald
											<ref target="MacDonald1904" type="bib">1904</ref>:
										34–35). In the absence of more detailed evidence, any
										explanation as to how he came to interact with the Sinclairs
										and their manuscripts must remain speculative.</p>
									<p>Domhnall Gorm's hand is neat, professional, and his command
										of the orthography, language, and poetics of the learned
										classes appears on the whole to be sound. The possibility
										that the quatrain and signature were inscribed for Domhnall
										Gorm should be borne in mind. Assuming it is Domhnall Gorm's
										own hand, this is an interesting specimen of aristocratic
										high-level literacy.</p>
									<p comment="Other Activities"> No other works in this hand, or
										attributed to Domhnall Gorm, are known. </p>
								</note>
							</handNote>
						</handDesc>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin>
							<p>A note in the main body of <ref type="ms" target="MS8">Arch. Seld.
									B.24</ref> refers to James IV as king, meaning production of the
								manuscript must have been begun sometime after 1488 (Boffey et al.
									<ref type="bib" target="Boffey1997">1997</ref>: 4). The
								appearance of the date 1592 on fol. 231<hi rend="sup">v</hi>, among
								the spare leaves towards the end of the manuscript, imply that it
								was complete by this date, although this is uncertain.</p>
						</origin>
						<provenance><p>It is thought that it was produced for the Sinclair family in
								either Edinburgh or Roslin (Boffey et al. <ref type="bib"
									target="Boffey1997">1997</ref>: 11).</p></provenance>
						<acquisition><p>The manuscript was bequethed to the Bodleian Library as part
								of the collection of John Selden (1584–1654) (Brown <ref type="bib"
									target="Brown1899">1899</ref>: 93). How it came to be in his
								collection is not known but the window between his collecting
								activities and the window in which the manuscript was composed is
								sufficiently narrow for there not to have been a significant
								intervening history.</p></acquisition>
					</history>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Bardic poetry</term>
					<term>Elegy</term>
					<term>Fragment</term>
					<term>Scottish scribe</term>
					<term>Scottish manuscript</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change when="2018-05-28" who="EPT">Initial draft of text transcribed and marked up from
				manuscript; draft introduction written.</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div n="1" type="verse" resp="Hand21" corresp="MS8.1">
				<pb n="231v" xml:id="MS8.231v"/>
				<lg n="1" type="stanza" xml:id="MS8.1.1">
					<l n="a" xml:id="MS8.1.1a"><lb n="4" xml:id="MS8.231v.4"/>
						<gap reason="damage" extent="2" unit="syllables" resp="EPT"/><w lemma="ar"
							lemmaRef="http://www.dil.ie/3902" ana="prep"
							comment="This may be the final syllable of a longer word, rather than a word in itself."
							>air</w><note type="fn" resp="EPT"><p>The visibility of text drops to
								zero to the immediate left of the "a-" of "air", means that this
								might be the ending of a longer word (three syllables maximum)
								rather than the preposition <hi rend="italics">air</hi>. In fact,
								lines ab, as now visible, are missing one of the two required
								perfect internal rhymes, and a word ending in "-uair" (: "buain")
								would supply such a rhyme. Nothing more can be said about this
								hypothesised word, unfortunately.</p></note><space type="scribal"
							/><w lemma="cith" lemmaRef="http://www.dil.ie/9259" ana="noun">cio<abbr
								cert="high">t<g ref="g4">h</g></abbr></w><space type="scribal"/><w
							lemma="in" lemmaRef="http://www.dil.ie/28194" ana="art">na</w><space
							type="scribal"/><w lemma="coinne" lemmaRef="http://www.dil.ie/10358"
							ana="noun">coinne</w><pc>.</pc><space type="scribal"/><note type="fn"
							resp="EPT"><p>Some pen strokes are visible just above this line, before
								the page becomes too damaged for anything to be made out. It is
								possible that they are abbreviation strokes relating to this line
								(e.g. "na" could be "na<hi rend="italics">m</hi>"). However, this
								doesn't produce any significantly more satisfying readings and
								letter forms, of which these marks could be the lower portions, can
								just about be made out above. </p></note>
					</l>
					<l n="b" xml:id="MS8.1.1b">
						<w lemma="do" lemmaRef="http://www.dil.ie/17096" ana="prep, art"
							>don</w><space type="scribal"/><w lemma="bith"
							lemmaRef="http://www.dil.ie/5971" ana="noun"><abbr cert="high">b<g
									ref="g4">h</g></abbr>io<abbr cert="high">t<g ref="g4"
								>h</g></abbr></w><space type="scribal"/><w lemma="for"
							lemmaRef="http://www.dil.ie/23272" ana="prep"><abbr cert="high"><g
									ref="g11">air</g></abbr></w><space type="scribal"/><w
							lemma="búain" lemmaRef="http://www.dil.ie/7248" ana="vnoun"
							>buain</w><space type="scribal"/><w lemma="a"
							lemmaRef="http://www.dil.ie/3" ana="poss">a</w><w lemma="duille"
							lemmaRef="http://www.dil.ie/19115" ana="noun">duille</w>
					</l>
					<l n="c" xml:id="MS8.1.1c"><lb n="5" xml:id="MS8.231v.5"/>
						<gap reason="damage" extent="2" unit="syllables" resp="EPT"/><choice>
							<sic><w lemma="bruach" lemmaRef="http://www.dil.ie/7041" ana="noun"
										><unclear reason="damage" cert="medium" resp="EPT"
										>b</unclear>ruai<abbr cert="high">c<g ref="g4"
									>h</g></abbr></w></sic>
							<corr resp="EPT"><w lemma="bruach" lemmaRef="http://www.dil.ie/7041"
									ana="noun"><unclear reason="damage" cert="medium" resp="EPT"
										>b</unclear>ruai<abbr cert="high">g<g ref="g4"
									>h</g></abbr></w></corr>
						</choice><note type="fn" resp="EPT"><p>The slenderisation suggests that this
								is a prepositional form, hence the tentative translation "{on the}
								bank".</p></note><space type="scribal"/><w lemma="lám"
							lemmaRef="http://www.dil.ie/29507" ana="noun">laim</w><space
							type="scribal"/><w lemma="fri" lemmaRef="http://www.dil.ie/24329"
							ana="prep">re</w><space type="scribal"/><w lemma="linn"
							lemmaRef="http://www.dil.ie/30274" ana="noun">li<abbr cert="high">n<g
									ref="g5">n</g></abbr>e</w><space type="scribal"
							/><pc>.</pc><space type="scribal"/>
					</l>
					<l n="d" xml:id="MS8.1.1d">
						<w lemma="fo-gaib" lemmaRef="http://www.dil.ie/22696" ana="verb">fu<abbr
								cert="high"><g ref="g11">air</g></abbr></w><space type="scribal"/><w
							lemma="sinn" lemmaRef="http://www.dil.ie/37607" ana="pron">si<abbr
								cert="high">n<g ref="g5">n</g></abbr>e</w><space type="scribal"/><w
							lemma="for" lemmaRef="http://www.dil.ie/23272" ana="prep"><abbr
								cert="high"><g ref="g11">air</g></abbr></w><w lemma="clár"
							lemmaRef="http://www.dil.ie/9377" ana="noun">clar</w><space
							type="scribal"/><w lemma="in" lemmaRef="http://www.dil.ie/28194"
							ana="art">na</w><space type="scribal"/><w lemma="cruinne"
							lemmaRef="http://www.dil.ie/13227" ana="noun">crui<abbr cert="high">n<g
									ref="g5">n</g></abbr>e</w>
					</l>
				</lg>
				<lg type="sig" xml:id="MS8.1.2">
					<l xml:id="MS8.1.2a"><lb n="6" xml:id="MS8.231v.6"/><w lemma="mise"
							lemmaRef="http://www.dil.ie/32365" ana="pron">misi</w><space
							type="scribal"/><name type="personal"><w lemma="Domnall"
								lemmaRef="http://www.dil.ie/18133" ana="noun">domnall</w><space
								type="scribal"/><w lemma="gorm" lemmaRef="http://www.dil.ie/26408"
								ana="adj">gorm</w><pc>.</pc></name></l>
				</lg>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
